<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the Fryday before Easter, commonly called good Friday, in the yeere of our Lorde. 1579. By Iohn Knewstub</title>
            <author>Knewstubs, John, 1544-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101374</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837190</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837190</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1505</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04905)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1505)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 994:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the Fryday before Easter, commonly called good Friday, in the yeere of our Lorde. 1579. By Iohn Knewstub</title>
                  <author>Knewstubs, John, 1544-1624.</author>
                  <author>Knewstub, John. Confutation of monstrous and horrible heresies, taught by H.N. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>At the three Cranes in the Vintree, by Thomas Dawson for Richard Sergier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed in London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The sermon was actually preached in 1576--STC.</note>
                  <note>First printed as part of: Knewstubs, John. A confutation of monstrous and horrible heresies, taught by H.N.</note>
                  <note>Trimmed at head, affecting running title and folio numbers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1505:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1505:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Sermon preached <hi>at Paules Croſſe the</hi> Fryday before Eaſter, <hi>commonly called good Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> in the yeere of <hi>our Lorde.</hi> 1579.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Iohn Knew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtub.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in London</hi> at the three Cranes in <hi>the Vintree, by Thomas</hi> Dawſon for Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Sergier. 1579.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1505:2"/>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:1505:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A Sermon preached at</hi> Paules Croſſe the Fryday before <hi>Eaſter, commonly called good Fryday, in</hi> the yeere of our Lorde. 1576.</head>
            <byline>
               <hi>By</hi> Iohn Knewſtub.</byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is thus writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (right Honorable and welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in our Sauiour Chriſte) by the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Chapter of his Epiſtle vnto <hi>Titus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11 The grace of GOD, that bringeth ſaluation vnto al men, hath appeared,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12 And teacheth vs that we ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vngodlynes, and worldly luſtes, and that we ſhoulde liue ſoberly, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and godly, in this preſent world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13 Looking for the bleſſed hope, and appearing of the glory of the mightie God, and of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14 Who gaue him ſelfe for vs, that he might redeeme vs from al iniquities, and purge vs to bee a peculiar people vnto himſelfe, zelous of all good woorkes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15 Theſe thinges ſpeake, and exhort, and rebuke with all authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1505:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This text doeth deuide it ſelfe into foure principal partes: The firſt part commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a teacher vnto vs, in theſe words: <hi>The grace of God that bringeth ſaluation, hath appeared and teacheth vs.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond declareth what it is that he teacheth vs, to wit, <hi>To deny vngodlines &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſtes, and to liue ſoberly, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; godly in this preſent world, wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the glorious appearing of Ieſus Chriſte.</hi> The third, noteth what coſt and charges the ſonne of God Chriſte Ieſus our Lorde and Sauiour was at, to haue vs good ſchollers, and to profite well in this doctrine, &amp; is conteined in theſe woordes: <hi>Who gaue himſelfe for vs, that he might redeeme vs from al iniquitie, and purge vs too bee a peculiar people vnto hym ſelfe, zelous of good workes.</hi> The fourth and laſt part, deſcribeth the order of this Schoole, &amp; the maner of teaching and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vp of Scholers, in theſe words: <hi>Theſe thinges ſpeake exhort,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 1.29.</note> 
               <hi>and rebuke with all authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning this Teacher (to reſolue you in few woordes,) It is the Goſpel of God, which is the power of God vnto ſaluation, for ſo many as ſhal beleeue it: And therfore
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1505:3"/>may wel bee called the grace of God that bringeth ſaluation. The comparing of this verſe, with the next before, wil let you plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, that it cannot bee otherwiſe ment, then of the worde of ſaluation, the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſte: Which for iuſt cauſes, is commended vnto vs vnder this glorious title of the grace of God that bringeth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. It is the Goſpel then, that teacheth vs to deny vngodlines, neither doth it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tel vs barely and nakedly what is to bee done. But with ſweete promiſes allureth, and with great perſwaſion &amp; moſt louing counſel &amp; aduiſe, doeth exhort &amp; prouoke vs therunto, crauing, beſeeching, &amp; intreating vs to yeelde and conſent: not leauing out any thing, that is likely to further the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that is in hande.</p>
            <p>The nature of man being (as it is) deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of knowledge, how can he but be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnto vs, that profeſſeth to teache. If there were no more but the name of a Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, it were yenough to driue vs to ſome conſideration for the good entertainment of him, albeit we had neuer ſeene nor hearde the man before. But when theſe Teachers bring gifts with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the better to perſwade, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe become teachers &amp; perſwaders,
<pb facs="tcp:1505:4"/>to whom for all our welfare and happie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, we are wholy beholden, may their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe poſſibly (thinke you) be neglected, and not eſtemed of any, who hath but the leaſt ſparke of humanitie or good diſpoſition in him? And behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth with it our ſaluation, teacheth and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth vs, to deny vngodlyneſſe, &amp; worldly luſtes: and to liue ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent worlde.</p>
            <p>If you like Teachers, that perſwade &amp; enter into the hearts of men by giftes, you can not miſlike him, I am wel aſſured, that bringeth no leſſe gift then your ſaluation. If giftes doe commend, I thinke he is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently commended vnto vs, &amp; moſt true it is, that giftes and benefites, cannot but commend their Maiſters that bring them. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.14</note> 
               <hi>that a gift layde ſecretly and cloſly in the boſome of him that is offended with vs, is able to aſſwage an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger when it is growen ſo ſtrong, that it may be ſaid to haue ſinewes and bones.</hi> He ſaith more and beſides this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 17.8.</note> 
               <hi>That a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is as a precious ſtone, it proſpereth &amp; preuaileth, whetherſoeuer it turneth.</hi> Rewardes and giftes receiued, hold a man
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1505:4"/>as captiue and Priſoner vnto the geuer, ſo that hee is ſcarce his owne man, but ſeeth with an other mans eyes, and dealeth with an other mans handes, for he who commeth commended vnto vs by ſome rewarde and gifte, is able, as it were by ſome enchaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſet what coulour he will vpon his matter, and that ſo cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ningly, as the wyſeſt man that is of vs al, ſhal not bewray it. For doe we not reade in <hi>Deuteronomie, That rewardes blinde the eies of the wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dent.</hi> 16.1</note> 
               <hi>and peruert the wordes of the iuſt?</hi> And this is the cauſe, why in that ſame place, the Iudges are forbidden to take rewardes, for ſuch is the corruption of man, that he wyll not ſtick to perſwade his euil cauſe by thoſe meanes, yf he ſhal vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that the Iudge lyeth any whyt open on that part. But this infirmitie of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times furthereth his euil cauſe by gifts, may not ſo preiudice the holy Ghoſt, who is without al ſuſpition to commend euyl cauſes vnto vs, but that it ſhalbe alwayes lawfull for him to vſe what way of perſwaſion as ſhall beſt like hym: yea to enter vpon vs euen by giftes, and to cauſe the grace of GOD bringing with it our ſaluation, to intreate vs to deny vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:1505:5"/>and worldly luſtes: to ſee if that which is ſo pearcing of itſelfe, be able too touch vs: that which perſwadeth ſo greatly, be of force to preuaile with vs: that which oftentimes ſpeedeth in euill matters: may finde fauour with vs to promote the beſt things. For what hath he not obtained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, that by gifts hath continued to perſwade. And among gifts, there is ſome diuerſitie, ſome be more able to mooue vs,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> then others are ſome perſwade more effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually then others doe: For thoſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, haue alwayes been regarded aboue the reſt, that haue drawen vs out of ſome great danger, or haue comforted vs in ſome great extremitie. The memory of ſuch, is woont to be of greateſt continuance, and of moſt thankful reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance with vs. When <hi>Dauid</hi> would perſuade <hi>Bethſabe</hi> his wife that <hi>Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſhould be king after him, and put her out of al doubt, that ſhe neede neuer to feare the matter any longer, he pledgeth for the aſſurance of his worde, his thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto God, for ſuch benefites, as could not but binde his obedience: That is, his often deliuerance out of trouble. <hi>As the Lorde liueth (ſaith Dauid) who hath brought my ſoule out of aduerſitie, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1505:5"/>thy ſonne ſhal raigne after me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The benefites are not lightly regarded, that are receiued in aduerſitte: For the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſenſe and feeling of the miſerie, doeth greatly enhance the price thereof. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke away all occaſion of doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, when he pawneth for aſſurance of his word, ſo great a matter, as was his thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes for his deliuerance out of aduerſitie: For it could not be, that he ſhould forget to redeme ſo great a gage. And in this higheſt degree of gifts, commeth this benefite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto vs, for it is the grace of God that bringeth ſaluation: And bringing of ſaluation, prooueth our eſtate to haue been damnable before. It is not only miſerie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we were plunged in before this benefit came, but a miſerie of miſeries: for we were holden vnder the thraldome of death &amp; dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Such a benefite deſerueth thankfull reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, it ſpeedeth, where any perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion will preuaile: ſuch a gift, a man would thinke, ſhould find fauor, &amp; proſper whither ſoeuer it turneth. Hauing ſucceded ſo great and grieuous a miſerie: how can it, but haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſt of moſt bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful &amp; ſweete mercie: We may learne by this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath bin ſaid, what the cauſe is, why the holy ghoſt ſaith not ſimply
<pb facs="tcp:1505:6"/>The Goſpel teacheth and exhorteth vs: but ſayth the grace of God, which bringeth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, teacheth and exhorteth vs: for it is the Goſpel that he meaneth, and yet he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it, The grace of God that bringeth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: to make vs more mindeful of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This maner of perſwading by giftes and benefites, vſed of the holy Ghoſt: may learne vs a profitable leſſon, howe to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande temptations vnto ſinne whatſoeuer: to witte, by keeping freſh in memorie, the ſeuerall benefites of God towardes vs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them as bulwarkes, againſt our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſaultes, ſo that when they allure vs, we may thus anſwere them, The God who hath redeemed my ſoule from al aduerſitie, doeth forbid it me: The grace of God to whom I owe my ſaluation, doeth denie it vnto me: The goodnes of that God, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue receiued life, health, honour, wealth, deliuerance out of theſe and theſe troubles, preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the murtherer, euil to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue, and ſlaunderer, doeth deſire me, that for all the good will that euer he hath borne me, I would not conſent vnto it.</p>
            <p>If any Prince ſhould by ſpeciall pardon, deliuer a ſubiect fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, that by law and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1505:6"/>Iuſtice had deſerued it, and after aduaunce him to ſome place of honour in the Lande: hard and vnthankful were his heart, if thoſe ſutes eſpecially of the prince, which brought with them the remembrance of this mercie for their better enterteinment, ſhoulde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be regarded: and in verie deede, the benefites receiued from our God, ſhould be notes of reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance vnto vs, for his ſeueral ſutes againſt ſinne, and ſhoulde be alwayes at the albowe iogging of vs, to remember him, when ſinne would pull vs from him, And with theſe or ſuch like ſpeeches to ſounde in our eares: That Lord that tooke thee off the Ladder, when the ſentence of euerlaſting death had paſſed againſt thee, biddeth thee nowe remember him: that God who hath picked thee out of ſo great a multitude, that continue in their infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hardneſſe of heart and obſtinacie, and bleſſed thee with ſpeciall knowledge, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and confidence in him, nowe willeth thee not to forget him. It ſhall bee profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for vs, to beholde this in practiſe, which nowe in doctrine can not but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> warring with the wicked at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts
<pb facs="tcp:1505:7"/>of his Miſtres, who would haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed him to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit wickednes with her, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth off al her wicked aſſaults, with this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. For the very remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters good wil &amp; benefits towards him, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deleth him ſo, that he dare not aſſent vnto her ſhamefull demaund, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in reſpect of the iniurie, that he ſhould doe vnto a maiſter, ſo good and well deſeruing at his hands. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde</hi> (ſaieth <hi>Ioſeph</hi> vnto <hi>her</hi>) <hi>my maiſter knoweth not what he hath in the houſe with me, but hath committed all that he hath into my hande, there is no man in this houſe greater then I, neither hath he kept any thing from me, but onely thee, becauſe thou art his wife. How then can I do this great wickedneſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The benefites of his maiſter towardes him, ſeeme ſo great a matter in his eyes, that he would learne of that impudent and ſhameleſſe woman, if impudencie it ſelfe could happely find out any colour of reaſon or excuſe, for ſo great and grieuous an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: <hi>How then</hi> ſayth <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> after he had recited the great kindnes of his maſter) <hi>can I poſsibly doe ſo great wickedneſſe?</hi> not thinking otherwiſe, but that ſhameleſſenes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1505:7"/>it ſelfe, would bluſh at ſuch vnkindneſſe, and vnthankfulneſſe, as that was, &amp; with ſhame inough begin to giue ouer, as one who had nothing more nowe to aunſwere, in ſo foule a matter. There is no man ſo baſe, but in reſpect of ſome benefite receiued from God, hee ſpeaketh that ſometimes in his heart, which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> vttered in woorde: to witte, there is no man greater then I: but there are fewe that inferre therevpon, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did, how then can I doe ſuch wickedneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, that hath made me the greateſt. It were a godly aduauntage had of Pride, to make this gaine of our mounting and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring thoughts, which would perſwade vs that we be the greateſt: and thus to replie vpon them: If I bee ſuch a one, howe then can I lie ſleeping in ſecuritie, ignoraunce of God, and his worde, malice and vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: being ſworne enemies to his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that hath thus aduaunced me? You ſee by this that hath beene ſayd, what is the vſe of God his benefites, euen to be the bane of vngodlineſſe, &amp; to ſmite thorowe this old man of ours, this corrupt nature: directing the Speare of Gods grace, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the heart roote of Sinne, when it ſtirreth within
<pb facs="tcp:1505:8"/>vs: So that ſinne ſhall no ſooner put out the head, but we (calling to mind ſome one, or other ſpeciall benefite of God) ſhall bee readie with that ſame weapon of his grace, to runne vpon it, and wound it at the heart. Therefore we ſee what neceſſitie lieth vpon vs, (except we wil exceede in all vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe) to yeeld our ſelues obedient ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers vnto this Teacher: euen the grace of God which bringeth ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Hauing ſpoken thus much of the ſchole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter, order requireth to tell you what the leſſon is, which this good Schoolemaiſter, would ſo gladly learne vs, and that is this: <hi>To denie vngodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and to liue ſoberly, iuſtly, and godly, in this preſent worlde.</hi> Let vs ſee what this great grace requireth of vs, euen deniall of vngodlineſſe, and worldly luſtes. Thus doth the ſpirit of God begin with vs, for we are ſo wretched and wicked matter, that we muſt be weeded ere any thing may ſafely be ſowen or planted in vs. This monſtrous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion &amp; Leproſie are we admoniſhed of, in the order of teaching, vſed by the holy ghoſt, generally throughout the ſcripture. In the Moral law, almoſt all precepts were nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1505:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thou ſhalt do no murther: Thou ſhalt not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit adulterie: Thou ſhalt not ſteale. &amp;c. to declare that the chiefe goodneſſe of a Chriſtian, is to haue conquered moſt euil in himſelfe: and that man to be the beſt, that hath drained his corruption moſt: I meane that hath driuen moſt corruption out of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, &amp; holden his affections in moſt ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and obedience. <hi>Dauid</hi> demanding how he may do good of a yong man, ſetteth out his meaning in theſe wordes: <hi>Where with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſhall a yong man clenſe his wayes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> after he hath greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended wiſdom, not finding any thing of ſufficient value to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it by, nor any creature that can point out the place vnto him, and ſay, here is the breed of it: in few words cloſeth vp the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; ſaith: <hi>To depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euil is vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> So that a man, who doth not weed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil out of him, can neuer looke for any good of that he hath ſowne. But let vs come vnto the particulars: we muſt deny vngodlineſſe. What vngodlines is, I can not better tell you, then by opening who be vngodly men, as they are deſcribed at large in the <hi>21.</hi> of <hi>Iob. They ſay vnto god, depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy waies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 21.</note> 
               <hi>who is the Almightie that wee ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:1505:9"/>ſerue him? and what profit ſhall we haue, if we pray vnto him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt note of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, <hi>They ſay vnto the Lord, depart from vs.</hi> Not that they are growne to ſuch wickedneſſe, as that this ſhould be the ſpeech of the to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue, but the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the heart: neither yet that ſimplie they would haue God goe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, but that they would meet him, &amp; be acquainted with him, without his worde: For they ſay, <hi>We deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes.</hi> That this is the true meaning, that they do not other wiſe put the Lord fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not deale with him in his word, is appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the next chapter: where <hi>Elephas</hi> reputing <hi>Iob</hi> among the vngodly, &amp; willing him to acquaint himſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God: vſeth theſe wordes: <hi>Receiue the law at his mouth, &amp; lay vp his wordes in thy heart.</hi> The Lord may not be deuided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Law for that is to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fforme him, &amp; to ſunder him from himſelfe, his wiſdome being a part of himſelf, &amp; to make an Idol of him. Yet is no thing ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, as to do thoſe dueties of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utre which perteine vnto him, or vnto our brethren, without conſulting or conferring with the word. For to let the Papiſts alone who do tranſubſtanciate the word, both into
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1505:9"/>a forraine tongue, and alſo into a ſtraunge ſenſe: Howe many be there among vs, that goe into great matters at aduenture (as they ſay) euen led by the common and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courſe of cuſtome, becauſe they haue beene ſo accuſtomed,<note place="margin">Prou. 20.18</note> notwithſtanding that <hi>Solomon</hi> doth teach vs, not to let thoughts tary in the hearte, but ſuche as haue beene placed there, by counſel and authoritie from the worde: and ſo doeth hee thinke alſo of warre, and chargeth vs, that we ſhould not enterpriſe it, but by counſel from the word. Which both of them, might ſeeme of due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to pleade priuiledge, and to claime par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in regarde of the ſodaine comming, &amp; vnaduiſed burſting out of them.</p>
            <p>Nowe when it commeth to paſſe, that we are particularly preſſed by the woorde, to let goe any pleaſure or profite, that wee long enioyed, who ſeeth not then, how with ful mouth wee crye, depart from vs, we wil none of thy waies? Then you ſee there is no remedie, but we muſt hold the Lord faſt to vs in his worde, for it hath ben alwayes the commendation of the godly, to haue wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with God. We are not ſaide to walke with God according to his infinite Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie &amp; Eſſence, neither yet in that ſenſe are
<pb facs="tcp:1505:10"/>we ſaide to depart from him, for his diuine being, doth not ſhew it ſelfe vnto creatures, neither is hee viſible vnto vs, but hee hath drawne nie vnto vs in his worde, &amp; we muſt walke with him by that. For how ſhall we feare that corrupt o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is ſo naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffed in vs, if his preſence do not fray vs from it? And what chriſtian, who any whit hath knowne his owne infection, dare but once dreame, that his preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by his word, ſhoulde not bee greatly needfull, to awake him often, and rouſe him out of the ſleepe of mind, while he vnderſtandeth by the worde euer and anon: that the Lorde goeth quite contrary to him, and is departed altogether from him. Wee are therefore to queſtion with the worde of God: how fareth it with me in this deede? am I gone from my god? haue I in diſpleaſure taken my leaue of my Lord? haue I driuen my Sauiour farre out of my ſight? Can it be wel with me, while my God turneth his barke on me? But when men liue without remorſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence, while they cannot abide once to loke vpon them ſelues, in the glaſſe of God his worde, while it is death for them, once to examine their doinges, doe they not ſay depart from vs, we wil none of thy wayes?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1505:10"/>When <hi>Ieremie</hi> the Prophete in in his <hi>8.</hi> Chapter, would note out the deſperate ſtate of the people in his time, he ſetteth no other marke vpon them but this: <hi>There is no man that ſaith what haue I doone:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but euery one turneth to their raſe, as the horſe ruſheth to the battaile.</hi> Then there is no way, vnleſſe we would ioine with this deſperate people, but that we muſt ſtil hold God before vs in the light of his worde, and often come into his preſence, while wee take at ſundrie times the accountes of our doinges by the worde: accounting not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the worde of God,<note place="margin">Eſay. 30.<hi>1.</hi>
               </note> for the generall duties of Chriſtianitie, but alſo for the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dueties, that our particular calling and place doeth bind vs vnto. We muſt needes conclude then, that vngodlineſſe reacheth further then to Turkes, Athieſts, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, who ſet the Lorde cleane beſide his word, euen to thoſe which without remorſe runne on, without any preſenting of them ſelues &amp; their deedes, before the preſence of his worde, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the Lord ſeeth to be ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we cannot want it, being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as vntoward ſcholers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil do nothing whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their maiſter his eie is not vpon them.
<pb facs="tcp:1505:11"/>therefore let vs al in the feare of God pray that we may haue loue vnto the worde, and liking to be in the ſight of our God, which is, when we haue our luſt and longyng, to be vnder the gouernment of the Goſpell. This is it, that <hi>Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſpendeth ſo muche time about, in the Prouerbes: vrgyng ſtil, that <hi>Wiſedome muſt delight vs,</hi> and finde ſome louing entertainment with vs: and that wee neuer ſo pleaſe our ſelues in our towardneſſe, as to imagine, we could long want this neceſſarie helpe of his preſence. Vnto this familiar conuerſation with God in his woorde, he promiſeth all bleſſinges, and deliueraunces from the greateſt daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. We muſt deny this vngodlines, that ſpeaketh theſe woordes vnto the Lord: <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from vs, for we deſire not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy wayes.</hi> What wickedneſſe were it, either with the Papiſt, to ſet a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour vpon the Lord his face, and to make him looke as we liſt: either els with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure an careleſſe Chriſtian, to let him looke as he liketh, ſo we neede not to looke vpon him? The Lorde hath planted the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the woorde in his Church, not onely to teach vs barely, but alſo to comfort vs in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1505:11"/>our iourney, and to quicken vs in our due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yea, and to feare vs alſo from ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who is the Almightie, that we ſhould ſerue him?</hi> This is a ſecond note of vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, an vſual ſpeache of vngodly hearts, howe ſo euer the tongue bee cleare of it. For in deede they haue no inward acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce with him, neither doe they in trueth ſee any ſuche deſertes towardes them, why why they ſhoulde be ſeruauntes vnto him. The benefits they haue, they ſee them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with other, but as for any ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard had of them, they doe not vnderſtand of it, and while they ſee nothing in God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde them, but that is generall vnto all, they aſcribe nothyng vnto him, but a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall kinde of goodneſſe, which they take to be indifferently caſt downe among men: to be taken vp of ſo many as will. Beſides this, they neuer accquainte them with the ſight of their ſinnes, and the deſert thereof, which ſhoulde leade them into a miſliking of themſelues, &amp; let them ſee other wages then benefites, to be by al equitie and right due vnto them. Thus it falleth out, that they would haue him ſhew, wherin he hath ſo hounde them, as hee might demaunde ſo
<pb facs="tcp:1505:12"/>great things of them: as if they ſhould call for a reckoning, to ſee what is come in, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the charges ariſe ſo great, and the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties laide vpon them, ſo many and diuerſe. Thus while the vngodly receiue benefites, but not as tokens of fatherly affections, while in the vſe of the benefite, they are no whit confirmed in the peculiar care and affection, which he beareth his elect, they cannot but ſay: <hi>Who is the Almighty that we ſhould ſerue him?</hi> What token haue we of his ſpecial good wil, why we ſhoulde in ſuch difficult matters ſerue him, &amp; with ſuch danger attend vpon him? For in very deede, he that ſhall get out more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ſeruice, had neede ſee more then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good will in him, who ſhall exact it. They enioy the benefite as other doe, but ſo as they doe repoſe them in it, and returne no ſpeciall thing into the accountes of the benefactour, wherby they might know hee maketh an other reckoning of them, then of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort: euen ſuch as a louing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeth of his owne ſonne. Moreouer, their ſinnes are ſeldome or neuer in their ſight, I meane with this conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that in iuſtice they doe deſerue, not onely the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1505:12"/>ſtopping of the courſe of his grace: but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to haue let in vpon them, the fluddes of his wrath. Which thing if it were truely ſeene, could not but ſet a great price vppon thoſe benefites, that come in ouer ſuche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertes. The minde of the geuer, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth not the gift of them, for they ſee not ſo far: they ioyne them not as ſeales to his letters of free grace, I meane, to the free graunt of his grace: notwithſtanding, we be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned of this diuiding of them, and ſo ſtraightly charged to vnite them: <hi>Beware leaſt thou ſay in thine hearte, my power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut, 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 18.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; the ſtrength of mine owne hand pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared me this aboundance, but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Lord thy God. For it is he which geueth the power to get ſubſtance, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh his couenant, which he ſware vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fathers, as appeareth this day.</hi> Is it not a great villanie, to taſte ſo liberally of his benefies, and yet to perſwade vs ſo ſparingly of his good wil? to haue ſo friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dealing with his giftes, &amp; ſo litle liking of him ſelfe, that when we haue deucured ſo many benefites, wee ſhoulde inquire of the Almightie, who he is, that wee ſhoulde ſerue him, as if yet we had ſeene nothing, to
<pb facs="tcp:1505:13"/>binde our ſeruice vnto him? Can there bee more vnkindneſſe, then in ſo many benefits beſtowed, to gayne no good will? ſo many benefits to be let out, &amp; no good wil to come in with them agayne? That wee may the more clearely ſee into his good will, &amp; free mercy through his benefites, wee muſt bee brought backe now &amp; then vnto our ſinnes, and the iuſt deſertes thereof. For then ſhal we reckon them to bee benefites in deede, when wee ſee what doeinges they haue ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, and beene ioyned withall. Thus allayeth <hi>Moſes</hi> the pride of the people of Iſrael, and getteth GOD his due honor among them in the ix. of <hi>Deuteronomie, Speake not thou in thy heart, (after the Lorde thy God hath caſt them out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee) ſaying:</hi>
               <note place="margin">eut. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>For my righteouſneſſe the Lord hath brought me in, remember and forget not, how thou prouokeſt the Lorde God to anger in the wilderneſſe, ſince the day thou diddeſt depart out of the lande of Egypt, vntyl ye came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this place: yee haue rebelled againſt the Lorde.</hi> Hee calleth to minde ſundry of their grieuous cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time &amp; the place. By theſe rules let
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1505:13"/>vs trie, who in matters of any weight laide vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Lord, are like to returne this anſwere: <hi>Who is the Lorde that I ſhoulde ſerue him?</hi> Euen ſo manie as doe finde, no ſweeteneſſe nor taſt in him by his benefites, as are no more confirmed by his bleſſings, in his fatherly affection towards them: ſuch as get thereby no ſtrength of fayth: ſuch as do not hold themſelues, the more bound vnto him: as are not the more delighted in him: as are not the more deſirous to walke worthie of him: as finde not their heart the more inyfull in him: as finde them no better min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his law, to the which he hath ſet ouer his owne loue: euen thoſe I ſay, that dwell in the benefites, &amp; ſo they haue their deſire, they holde that their heauen, and their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe: that looke no further then the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, that ſtay vpon it, and inquire no further whether God do loue them, and is become a father vnto them, ſo as they may accounte vpon his benefites, as giftes from a louing father: thoſe that thinke themſelues then to vſe his benefites beſt, when God and all goodneſſe is the furtheſt from their minde: thoſe that can finde no taſte in theſe tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bleſſings, vnleſſe the mention of him
<pb facs="tcp:1505:14"/>who giueth the taſte and ſauour vnto them, be indented and conditioned withall, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part farre from them, for that time which they haue to vſe them: thoſe that will neuer ſet their ſinnes in ſight, that they may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the accounte of the benefite, and the good will of the benefactour. Wee muſt denie this vngodlineſſe, that yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, <hi>Who is the Lord, that wee ſhould ſerue him?</hi> After ſo long vſe of his benefites.</p>
            <p>Now would I knowe, where we might haue a place for them, that are leſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him, then they were manie yeares agoe, who haue leſſe comfort in his worde, leſſe Religion, leſſe obedience, leſſe good conuerſation: as for them that take his benefits, and with them doe warre againſt him, their place is taken vp alreadie in the nethermoſt pit, if the Lorde giue not great repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cance: therfore brethren for Gods cauſe let vs haſten our beeter acquaintance with him, who by benefits, hath ſo long time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him ſelfe vnto vs, and let it be our ſhame that he ſhoulde thus long bee a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vnto vs, that of ſo long time hath had ſo louing dealing with vs. Let vs ioy more in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1505:14"/>his delights, ſet our heartes more vpon that he commandeth, and commendeth vnto vs: ſo ſhall we come out of their rancke, which in heart ſay: Who is the Lorde, that wee ſhould ſerue him? Which men by his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, haue receiued no earneſt of their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no pledge of any ſpeciall good wil, no aſſurance of true ſafetie, no delight in his loue, no more familiarite with him, nor greater comfort of him: who are no more drawne out of the worlde, and her delightes to follow him, who hath in ſo ſundrie giftes witneſſed his good will: called them vnto him, and pledged theſe as earneſts, that his owne glorie abideth for them.</p>
            <p>Now would I ſee where wee might ſet them, if not in his ranck who haue ſo often bene fetched vp from the loue of the world, by ſo many meſſengers of Gods mercie, and yet haue ſo little ioy to be aboue, and ſo hungerly purſue the pleaſures and profites here below, as if they had neuer (no not in meditation) had the ſight of any other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights. The benefites then lead vs vnto the Lorde, when in them we ſee him to bee our father, &amp; make the more haſt to come to him hauing an eye to the endleſſe life he calleth
<pb facs="tcp:1505:15"/>vs vnto: comming more in deſire from theſe things here below, and getting more holde, and more hope aboue: ſhewing as well in proſperitie as aduerſitie, that we are not wedded in our luſt and deſire, vnto worldly goodes, in wealth, by not beeing letted by it, to followe the way that God doeth ſet before vs, nor yet to deale mercifully with our neighbours, and to walke humbly with them: &amp; in affliction, by holding our ſelues well contented, inſomuch as we want not him who is a plentifull portion, and the beſt veritage.</p>
            <p>The laſt note of vngodlineſſe is this, they ſay, what profite ſhall we haue if wee call vpon him? Theſe are no ſpeeches of the tongue, as I haue ſaide before, but the ſenſe of the heart. No man ſo euill that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not ſome reckoning of his prayers, howe ſome do value them, we cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant. The holy Ghoſt when he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued the people, for their out warde wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in ſacriſices, willeth them to call vpon the Lorde in the day of trouble, promiſing that he will heare them: and they ſhall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him:<note place="margin">ſal. 50.</note> making prayer a ſpecial worſhip of God, and ſetting it before the outwarde
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1505:15"/>ſacrifices, in the <hi>4.</hi> of <hi>Deut.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note> it is made the peculiar prerogatiue of the people of God, becauſe there are none in ſuch a caſe as they be, who haue their Gods ſo nigh them, as our God is nigh vnto vs, in all that we call vnto him for. Then muſt it needes be, that they are in an euill taking, that ſee no fruit of their prayers: it being the ſpeciall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the people of God, to haue him nigh in their prayers, by graunting their peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But for aſmuch as it is ſayd to be the voice and affection of the heart, and no man being aſked, wil giue out ſo ſlenderly of his praiers: Let vs come to a further exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of it. The moſt ſort of men, haue no profite by their prayers, becauſe they make not conſcience to knowe and doe thoſe things, which the Lorde by his worde hath reuealed, to be pleaſing in his ſight: <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we aske,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.22.</note> (ſayth. S. <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of him, becauſe we keepe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements: and doe thoſe thinges which are pleaſing in his ſight.</hi> No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail then if thoſe be farre from hauing their prayers heard of the Lorde, who haue nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowledge nor liking of his woorde. And a great ſort of others, who in profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:1505:16"/>haue receiued his woorde, when they want any thing, if they ſee meanes how to come by it, either pray not at all, but forthwith vſe the meanes: either elſe, if they pray, it is but of faſhion, as being in their iudgement ſure and ſafe alreadie: if they ſee no likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hodde to attaine it, being without hope, they let praier fal. So if any thing fal out, where there was the worke of an ordinarie meane, it ſteppeth betweene God and his prayſe, &amp; darkeneth the light of prayer: If otherwiſe any thing come, where prayer for want of fayth was let downe, that is put ouer to miracle or fortune: therefore in heart and of experience they cannot ſay, that they are anie whitte beholding vnto their prayers. But we learne in the Booke of God, that the godly pray in matters moſte harde to be brought to paſſe, and moſt vnlikely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of anie vſuall and ordinarie meanes: and yet are heard, and giue him the praiſe. There are named in the <hi>107.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>107.</hi>
               </note> Pſalme, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers matters that ſeeme to be mere caſual, comming without all meanes, yet prayed for, graunted, and with prayſe returned to the giuer: and vnder thoſe are all other alſo vnderſtood, that may be thought to be as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1505:16"/>There is mention made of the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the Sea, toſſed with tempeſts, now hoyſed vp, nowe plunged downe, till their heartes faile within them: yet when they pray vnto the Lorde, they are heard of him, and then do they giue him thankes. Other caſuall things are mentioned, and all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended. But in the laſt verſe the holie Ghoſt, maketh it only the wiſe and godlie mans worke, to vnderſtand this, in trueth to comprehend it, and by true and inwarde aſſurance thereof to giue him the prayſe for it. The vngodly therfore in ordinary things are hindred by the meanes: inextraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie they ſee nothing but chance: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſay: <hi>What profite ſhall we haue if we pray?</hi> The children of God, knewe that nothing is pure vnto them, vnleſſe it be ſanctified with prayer: and therefore they reforte to him in all their neceſſities by prayer. They poure their griefes into his boſome, with deſire to obteine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Tim. 3.</note> that they might prayſe his mercies, and they ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde, if they continue aſking, either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liueraunce, either elſe a tollerable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which doth aſſure them, that it is not in vaine to ſeeke the Lorde, and that the ende
<pb facs="tcp:1505:17"/>will be happie. Praier for benefites, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth God to be the giuer, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth prayſe to bee giuen in trueth: not to pray to God, is to be an vtter enimie to his glorie: not to pray particularly, as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie requireth, is to enuie him &amp; his praiſe, and the practiſe of <hi>Dauid</hi> (in particular conſiderations making his prayers and Pſalmes) doeth reprooue it. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts take God his grace to bee throwne downe indifferently. And men not experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced of his goodneſſe particularly, muſte needes thinke, that he hath put all thinges vnto a generall gouernment, for as for anie particular experience, of his good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes them, they haue it not. Wee muſt denie this vngodlineſſe, that groweth by prayer, into no experience of God his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Doe we thinke that any man, ſhall euer fafely put himſelfe ouer vnto the hope of the promiſes, at the houre of death: which all his life long, he neuer tried to be true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Wee muſt alſo denie worldly luſtes, and not onely thoſe, which tende to hurt our neighbour, in bodie, goods, or good name: but euen thoſe that holde vs ſo in this world, as we can get no true taſte in the pleaſures
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1505:17"/>of an other: For we are holden captiue of worldly luſtes, in one reſpect or other: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll we become newe creatures, looking for that glory, which ſhall appeare at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſte. The next thing required is to liue ſoberly. This ſobrietie, is a gifte that moderateth the minde in his delights and affections, and may therefore well bee termed The moderatour of the minde. It is a gift, that doeth keepe the minde from pleaſures altogether vnlawful: &amp; in that theſe bee lawful, it keepeth a man from the exceſſe &amp; abuſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That it is not onely reſtrained to the filthie deſires of the fleſh, may be procued in the xii. to the <hi>Romans:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> Where the Apoſtle appointeth this gyfte and grace of God, to order euery man in his calling, that he take not vpon him, but according to that meaſure which God hath geuen him. For in very deede, the minde of man hath many thinges, beſides the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy deſires of the fleſhe, too ouerturne it, wherein this gift of God hath good vſe. It was this gift that Paule had, when as hee profeſſed him ſelfe to haue learned, to bee riche, and to bee poore: to haue beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, to abounde, and alſo to want: to
<pb facs="tcp:1505:18"/>to be content with all eſtates, and to holde hymſelfe happy in them, as in a portion ſent him from the Lord. It may be thought no great gift, for a rich man to learne to be rich, yet doeth the Apoſtle ſay, it is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that requireth learning, and doeth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe it vnto Chriſt his worke within him. It is therfore worth the labour, to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome farther conſideration, what hee ſhould meane in this matter. The meaning he geueth in the ſame place, when he ſaith: <hi>I haue learhed in what eſtate ſoeuer I am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> 
               <hi>therewith to be content.</hi> A leſſon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. A leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neceſſarie for rich men, to learne them to be riche: that is, to hold them ſelues contented, to remember they haue theyr bondes appointed them, and there to acquaint their affections, to finde contentation, ſufficiencie, and a ryche portion. So ſhal they truely be thankful to God for it. For in very deede theſe heartes of ours muſt finde them in their owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion richly prouided for, ere they ſhal in crueth and vnfainedneſſe bee ioyful in the Lord. Let vs then learne from a contented minde to ſay vnto our heartes: This is thy lot appointed thee of the Lorde, heere are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1505:18"/>thy boundes, this eſtate hath the Lorde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed vnto thee, There is good cauſe, not onely to be content, but alſo wel apaide with it. We muſt learne our heartes to be content with it, nay to take it as riche and liberal portions whatſoeuer it be, and as a barre to holde in our affections from raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging into greedy deſires. For our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are as guifes, vnſatiable, that woulde neuer reſt with contentation in a thing, but ſtill be enflamed with the deſire of more, which would ſtil draw and hale vs forward and ſo holde vs in continuall torment. The remedy where of, the Lord hath appointed our owne eſtate whatſoeuer to be: that it might appeaſe our affections, and ſettle them with the reſt, peace and good liking, as in the ſeate which our good God hath ſeene to be conuenient for vs, and therefore ſet vs in it, to finde eaſe, quiet, comfort and contentment therein. For if thine heart be not ſetled in thine eſtate, with good liking &amp; contentation, as in a good prouiſion: it is vnpoſſible, that euer thou ſhouldeſt become thankful for it. For to ſeeme to ioy without ioy, is to play y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hypocrite, &amp; to diſſemble w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God. We muſt therfore take our ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:1505:19"/>to be riche already, and let goe this deſire to be riche:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Tim. 6.</note> For as <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, <hi>They that deſire to be riche, fall into ſnares &amp; noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome luſtes, which drowne men in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition &amp; deſtruction, which while ſome haue luſted after, they haue erred from the faith.</hi> Wee muſte let goe the ſeeking greedly after that we haue found already: for there is riches &amp; ſufficient treaſures in euery eſtate, which muſt be founde out of vs to quenche this deſire to bee riche. Let vs learne to be content with our eſtate, and to hold that as a certaine rule, for he that hath no ſure rule, ſhalbe ſo toſſed of his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; ſo carried hither &amp; thither, as he ſhal neuer finde a time to ſay, it behooueth me to hold my ſelfe here within my bondes. Let euery man with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> learne therfore to be rich, &amp; to take vp good liking of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and eſtate, and take heede he conuey not the title of true thankfulneſſe from his God, while the vnquiet deſire of encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his condition, ſtealeth all comfort, which muſt be matter of true thankfulnes, from his preſent eſtate. But we muſt learne alſo with <hi>Paule</hi> to bee poore, as well as to be riche, for he had learned, and wee muſte
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1505:19"/>in what eſtate ſoeuer wee bee, therewith to bee contented. And this contentation of mindeis a medicine for coue touſnes,<note place="margin">Hebr. 13.</note> as the Apoſtle teſtifieth, ſaying: <hi>Let your conuerſation be without couctouſneſſe, being content with that you haue.</hi> The riche man muſt bee learned to bee poore, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen to be ready with contentation of heart to goe vnder a poore eſtate, and to aſſure him ſelfe to finde the Lordes bleſſing and comfort in it. Hee muſt in his riches take out this leſſon, &amp; ſchoole himſelfe herein, &amp; by exerciſe and meditation acquaint his minde to the liking of a lower eſtate, yf the Lorde ſhoulde be ſo good: hoping to finde the Lorde very good vnto him in the ſame. Behold a meditation in riches, &amp; a leſſon that is of all men to be ſtudied, and not that onely, but learned alſo, &amp; taken out: that yf theyr eſtate ſhoulde yet bee poorer, they ſhoulde perſwade them ſelues to finde the Lord good vnto them, in that their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore before to make theyr reckoning of a poorer eſtate, by much me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of it, and yet a rich bleſſing in that notwithſtanding, euen a quiet &amp; a conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted minde. And this would further the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="tcp:1505:20"/>of our preſent eſtate, when we ſhould aſſure our ſelues, of a very good portion &amp; plentiful, yf our eſtate were yet lower. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought we ſo to learne it, as a leſſon not likely to come to prartice: but as one, whoſe practice were not like to be deferred. This leſſon hath in it, a very neceſſarie vſe to trie vs by. For whatſouer hee bee, that cannot beare a lowe eſtate layde vpon hym by the Lorde: yf he haue an higher, he wil abuſe that in like maner. For he that is aſhamed of pouertie, wilbe proude of wealth. Hee that is vnpatient when he is humbled: wil be inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r, when he is exalted. For what can bynde him to true duetie, if it be not conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto GOD? which yf hee dare diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence withal in pouertie, he wyl not great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regarde in aboundaunce. Thus we ſee for a man to learne to be rich, it is expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent hee learne to bee poore. For a man to learne to bee honourable, it is required hee learned with pacience and contentation, to goe vnder an eſtate without honour. This ſobrietie then, that keepeth the mind from being ouercharged, and drunken with the deſire of a better eſtate: is principally and chiefly required in a Chriſtian, yet rea
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1505:20"/>cheth it further, and conteyneth within it thoſe, who albeit they bee not greatly ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng after an other or better eſtate, yet be they too much wrapped and intangled, in the cares and delights of that they already haue.</p>
            <p>This doeth the Apoſtle note vnto vs:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.30.31.</note> in the firſt to the <hi>Cor. This I ſay brethren, becauſe the time is ſhort hereafter, that both they whiche haue wyues, bee as though they haue none: and they that weepe, as though they wept not: and they that reioyſe, as though they reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not: and they that buye, as though they poſſeſſed not: And they that vſe this worlde, as though they vſed it not: for the faſhion of the world goeth away.</hi> And hee doeth not onely open the diſeaſe, but alſo geue vs the remedy of it: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the ſhortneſſe of this life, and the ſpeedy paſſage thereof. Whiche hee woulde haue to ſeaſon our ioy, to ſeaſon our delightes, euen our bying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng. As yf hee ſhoulde ſay, there were no place of ryght ioy, ryght griefe, true hying, true ſellyng, where the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the ſhortneſſe of this lyfe,
<pb facs="tcp:1505:21"/>and the ſtep of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other did not ſtep in, to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derat the ioy, the griefe, the bying &amp; ſelling the cares that doe accompanie a married eſtate. Howe needefull it is that we ſhould (euen in lawfull thinges) haue our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons temperate: The parable in the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>Luke</hi> doth apparanclie declare.<note place="margin">Luke. 14</note> Where they that are bidde to the Supper make their excuſes, only by thoſe thynges that of them ſelues are lawfull and permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For it is lawful to buye a Farme, it is lawful to prooue Oxen, it is lawful to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and to be married: Yet it is ſaide that rather the baſeſt of the people, ſhalbe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to enter in, then that theſe (who haue been bid and are hyndred by theſe thinges) (though in themſelues not vnlawful) ſhould caſte of the Supper. Wee ſee then howe needeful this ſobrietie is, that keepeth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſurfetting with theſe tranſitorie things. The very <hi>Ethnickes</hi> hane found &amp; taught that there is a bleſſing, which a good men hathmay iynde in euery eſtate. Seneca hath theſe woordes: <hi>Aſſueſcendum ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioni ſuae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">enecae de anquilitate itae.</note> 
               <hi>nihiltam acerbum, in quo non ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qus animus ſolatiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inueniet.</hi> If Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men founde ioy in euery eſtate, by cuſtome and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1505:21"/>contimiance, ſhall we finde none, who haue the promiſe of our GOD, for ſpecial bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges and aſiſtaunce. Let vs anſwere our affections, which will not heare of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing: as <hi>Dauid</hi> did <hi>Michol,</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Saule. 2. Sam. 6:</hi> who ſcornfully checking hym,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.</note> that hee had ſo abaſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in bringing home the Arke of the Lorde, and that before the maides of his ſeruauntes, receiued this anſweare from him: it was before the Lord, who choſe me rather then thy father, and al his houſe: and commaunded me to bee ruler ouer all the people of the Lorde: and therefore I wil yet be more byle then this, and wilbe lowe in my owne ſight: and of the very ſame maide ſeruants which thou haſt ſpoken of, ſhall I be had in honour. Let vs, I ſay, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare our affections, and ſay, it is before him, and for him, of whom we holde all: let vs ſay, wee are yet ready to be more vile and lowly, if neede require, and our God ſee it ſo good: for wee muſt cheyne vp our affections, with conſideration that our bondes are limitted vnto vs, and that wee are ready to be abaſed, yf ſuche a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhoulde he layd vpon vs, from the Lord.
<pb facs="tcp:1505:22"/>Let vs learne in the feare of God, to take vp our affections, from purſuyng theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bryng that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord hath pledged himſelfe for aſſurance of a ſufficient proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: <hi>Let your conuerſation be without couetouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for it is ſaide: I wyll not leaue thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> If wee had but the woorde of ſome wealthie man, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vnto vs a ſufficiencie, howe woulde it comfort our hartes, and leſſen our labours and cares? Beholde the woordes of the higheſt for him that is content with that he hath: yf this will not mooue vs, let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that in the eight of <hi>Luke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> there is mention made of a curſed kind of grounde, that receiued the precious ſeede of Gods worde into it: but either riches, cares, or voluptuous lyfe, doeth ſo choake it, as there commeth no fruite of it. And yf this wil not preuayle with vs, let vs cal to mind the watchwoorde that is geuen vs by out Sauiour Chriſte in the <hi>21.</hi> of <hi>Luke: Take heede leaſt at any time your heartes bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oppreſſed with ſurfeiting and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and cares of this life.</hi> Now if ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> happen to bee any, who beeing weery with the burden of theyr weakneſſe, in this par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:1505:22"/>ſhal become earneſt ſuters vnto the Lorde, to preuaile againſt theyr corruption in this behalfe: let them aſſure them ſelues that the vnfeigned petition and prayer of a man loaden with the burden of his want, being continued: cannot returne emptie from that GOD, who by name calleth out ſuche, to come vnto him, with promiſe that hee wyll heare them. Therefore to conclude this matter of ſobrietie, let our lot geuen vs of the Lorde, be our limitte, let a lower eſtate be wel digeſted by meditation: let GOD his aſſurarmce bee ſufficient, let his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings feare vs: let his promiſe (yf wee bee weery) incourage vs.</p>
            <p>To liue righteouſly, is ſo to order our life, as euery man may haue his owne at our hands: for iuſtice is a vertue that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his due. The lord to main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine brotherly loue among his, hath made one the ſtorehouſe of neceſſaries, for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: So is the welfare of euery man laid out of himſelf, that loue may by ſuch means rather bee mayntained. Hee that is in the place of iuſtice &amp; iudgement, is to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that he geue to euery man his owne. For the Fatherleſſe, in his good cauſe,
<pb facs="tcp:1505:23"/>hath the ryght of a father in him: The wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, of an huſbande: the blinde and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant man, that cannot diſcerne where the helpe of his cauſe lieth, hath the right and title of an eye in him: the oppreſſed of a Patrone. Thus doeth <hi>Iob</hi> cleere himſelfe, in the <hi>29.</hi> of <hi>Iob. I deliuered the poore that cried,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and the fatherleſſe, and hym that had none to helpe him, the bleſſing of him that was ready to peryſhe, came vppon me, and I cauſed the widowes hart to reioyce, I was the eie to the blind &amp; feete to the lame, I was a father to the poore, and when I knewe not the cauſe, I ſought it out diligently: I brake the iawes of the vnrighteous man, &amp; pluckt the pray out of his teeth.</hi> Thus did <hi>Iob</hi> diſcharge him, of the defence hee did owe vnto them: lendyng his eye vnto the blind. to ſpie out the right of his cauſe: and his hande to the oppreſſed, to plucke the pray out of the vnrightecus mans teeth. Mare and beſides this, the whole land hath title, to a defence and ſaftie by them fromſinne. Forſimre and wickednes vnpuniſhed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the lande giltie of blood, and bringeth the wrath of GOD vpon it. Which wee haue notably prooued vnto vs, in the <hi>21.</hi> of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1505:23"/>
               <hi>Dent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> A man is founde dead, it is not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen who ſine him, the elders and iudges muſt come foorth, and meaſure to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that are rounde about hym that is ſlayne: the Elders of the Citie next to the ſlayne man, muſt take a Heyfer out of the droue, and bring it into a ſtony valley, and ſtrike of the Heyfers necke: and waſhe theyr hands ouer the Heifer that is behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp; teſtifie, &amp; ſay: <hi>Our hands haue not ſhed this blood, neyther haue our eyes ſeene it: O Lord be merciful to thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Iſraell, and lay no innocent blood to the charge of thy People Iſrael, and ſo the blood ſhalbe forgeuen them: ſo ſhal yee take away crie of the innocent blood.</hi> This care and prayer was there, to vnburden the lande of blood: euen when the malefactour coulde not be founde, and this confeſſing of a kinde of guiltineſſe, in the Elders and Iudges, next vnto that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: for that (yf iuſtice had beene ſtraightly looked vnto by them) it is credible, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor durſt not haue approched ſo neare. Thus woulde the Lord teache vs, that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe vnpuniſhed, crieth out againſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wherein it is committed. Nowe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:1505:24"/>by the expreſſe commaundement of God, there was ſuche care taken to purge the land of murder, or manſlaughter, when the authour thereof was vnknowen: And that not otherwyſe, then by ſacrifice, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſolempne proteſtation before the Lorde, of theyr innocencie, eyther for doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng it, or ſeeing it done, they were diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of the daunger thereof: What conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and care ought yee, and all other that ſit in iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to haue, that you make not your ſelues, and this lande guiltie of the blood, by winking at ſinne and wickednes: eſpecially, by letting the murtherer that is manyfeſt eſcape you? And yf the whole land, (where wickedneſſe committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſecond Table, is winked at) bee founde guiltie of the blood: wee ſtande in greater danger of that iniquitie that direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly concerneth the glory of God: I meane the offences doone againſt religion, and the true woorſhyp of GOD: And the whole lande, is to looke for defence againſt ſo great daunger, at the Magiſtrate his hande. And becauſe it is a duetie they owe vnto vs, it ſtandeth them vpon to ſeeke the peace of their owne conſcience, in that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1505:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>calling: which cannot be other wife com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed, then in the true diſcharge of that: which is det and due on theyr behalfe. That which is recorded in the <hi>22.</hi> of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua,</hi> doth notably direct magiſtrates,<note place="margin">Ioſua. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> with what care and vigilancie, they are to deale againſt corruption, in the worſhip of God. It is woorth the notyng to obſerue, howe they were afrayde of the Altar erected by <hi>Iordan:</hi> inſomuche that they geathered them togeather, to goevy to warre againſt theyr brethren, ſo ſoone as they heard, that an Altar was builded in that place: Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it their brethren had no ill meaning in that matter. Naye as afterward they doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, their meaning therin was very good &amp; godly: but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience of duty, &amp; experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of plagues, where ſuche offences as there they feared, had eſcaped without puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: made them ielous ouer euery occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; afrayd of euery light ſuſpition: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the ſpeache, which they had to theyr brethren: <hi>Haue we to litle</hi> (ſay they) <hi>for the wickedneſſe of Peor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſua.</hi> 22.17.</note> whereof wee are not cleanſed vnto this day? yee are turned this day from the Lord: and euen to morowe hee wyll be wroth, with all the congregation of Iſraell.
<pb facs="tcp:1505:25"/>Did not Achan treſpaſſe greatly, in the execrable thing, and wrath fel on all the congregation of Iſrael, and this man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone periſhed not in his wickednes. The Lorde put it into the minde of our magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, in lyke maner: that when ſoeuer they ſhall heare of an Aultar erected, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſecrete corner of this land, &amp; falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp vſed, they make no delay, vntyll they haue ſeene the offence puniſhed. Wee ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what cauſe magiſtrates haue to watch ouer euill, and what occaſion wee haue to commend them to God, by feruent prayer, that they may ſincerely ſerue the Lorde, in ſo great a callyng, leaſte the whole lande ſhoulde be araigned, before the iudgement ſeate of the higheſt, and all found guiltie of much blood, outrage, and Idolatrie, which hath long laide vpon the land vnpunyſhed: which plague, the Lorde in mercy keepe farre from vs.</p>
            <p>Iuſtice and Iudgement, they are the ſtrong holdes, and fenced places of this land, they are the keyes of our Countrey. they keepe vs better then all the Blocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, or places of defence whereſoeuer: they are better able to encounter with our
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1505:25"/>enimies, then any garyſon of men, howe well practiſed ſoeuer they may bee. But contrarywiſe, the neglect of iuſtice, is woorſe then rebellion: it pulleth Princes out of theyr thrones, maketh the lande caſt out her inhabitants, ioyneth with forra ne power, openeth the gates of all our caſtles and houldes, taketh the weapon from the warriour, taketh the hart from the valiant Souldier, wiſdome and forecaſt from the wiſe Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cellour, poiſoneth al our munitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And in the fifth of <hi>Eſai,</hi> The Lorde vnder the ſimilitude of a Vine,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> doeth moſt liuely declare, how he wil deale with his people, when iudgement and righteouſneſſe can not be founde among them. He wil breake downe the wal thereof, and it ſhalbe troden downe, he will take away the hedge, and ſhalbe eaten vp. It is our part therefore to pray for our magiſtrates, &amp; thoſe that be in place of iuſtice, that they may looke to the cauſe of the Widowe, Fatherleſſe, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, that they may purge the lande of blood, by takyng puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours: that they may haue courage and the feare of GOD, that they may hate coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, ſo that our Prince may ſit ſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="tcp:1505:26"/>vs, our holdes ſtrongly fortified, our hedges ſtill vpholden, that we may long inioy peace, to the better honouryng of our God. And theyr owne ſafetie doeth require great care in this behalfe. <hi>Shalt thou reigne</hi> (ſaith the Prophet to <hi>Iehoikim</hi>) <hi>becauſe thou cloſeſt thy ſelfe in Cedar?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Did not thy father eate, drinke, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he executed iuſtice and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? when he iudged the cauſe of the poore hee proſpered: was not this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knewe me (ſaith the Lorde) but thine eies, and thy heart, are only for the couetouſneſſe, and for oppreſſion: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thus ſayth the Lorde of Iehoikim, he ſhalbe buried as an Aſſe is buried.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lawier he muſt deale iuſtly, &amp; geue euery man his owne: for hee is the liuing lande marke, that limitteth men their inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaunce, that pointeth out their right and title, howe farre it goeth, and ſo breaketh controuerſie, and telleth euery one in his doubtful cauſe, where his clayme and title lieth, what lawe and equitie wil beare him in, and where it will forſake him. Hee (I ſay) is a liuing lande marke, that by true o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of the lawes, boundeth euery man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1505:26"/>within the compaſſe of his owne title. And becauſe of that, doeth highly deſerue of the common wealth, as a moſt neceſſarie, and profitable member thereof. Suche men are the common treaſure houſe of the Lord, whereunto the euidences of euery man are committed: and they put in truſt withall, to reſerue for euery man his title: that when hee is incombred for his right, they ſhoulde out of that Treaſure houſe, of the lawe, bryng good euidence for him, and ſo foorthwith, cleare his innocencie. The lawe is the houſe of euery man, where bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toſſed with many ſtormes abroade, hee findeth a place to hide his head in, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng in ſafetie, doeth boldly contemne both winde and weather, &amp; quietly take his reſt. For being toſſed with iniuries, either in body, goodes, or name, we haue no houſe of refuge, &amp; reſt beſide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law: no ſanctuarie in our vniuſt vexation, beſides that. The place which they ſerue GOD in, who are mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the lawe, is very high and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: the good they may doe, very muche, yf GOD geue them conſcience and care of it. The hurt in lyke manner, is exceeding great, where the feare of God
<pb facs="tcp:1505:27"/>doeth not rule. For is it not a meruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous miſchiefe to remooue the landmarke of any man? It is that ſinne, that had a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne curſe, called for againſt it, by the miniſterie of the <hi>Leuites,</hi> whereunto al the people were commaunded to ſaye,<note place="margin">Dent. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> Amen. And what diuerſitie or difference is there betweene him, that ſetteth in the lande marke, and ſo boundeth a man ſhorter: and him, that eyther by wreſting of the lawe, or hyding the true meaning of it, is an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of cuttyng ſhort, or empayring the true Title of any man? Euery man wil graunt, that yf a man of no conſcience, had the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodie of all the Euidences of this lande, hee might doe muche miſchiefe, by cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, croſſing, interlining, putting in and out, at his pleaſure, hidyng, or ſhewyng, renting, or reſeruing, as him luſteth. And is not this perfourmed, whyle the lawe is made to ſpeake, that they knewe in trueth it did neuer meane: and too burye that in ſilence, which it was appointed to geue te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony and witneſſe vnto? And if all this were nothyng, what can bee ſo miſerable, as when a man hath ben al the day abrode, in the ſtormes, and tempeſtes, at night
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1505:27"/>when he commeth home, hee ſhal finde his houſe in that caſe, that it can neither holde out wind nor rayne? And do not many, who are forced by reaſon of the Stormes and Tempeſtes abroade, to take them to this their houſe and harborowe, I meane the Law: finde the tempeſt often as grieuous there, as before they dyd in the playne? woulde to God there were none turned out of theyr owne doores in the middeſt of the ſtorme, without any hope at all of harbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe from thence? or if a man that had ben dogged, to his owne doores, by Theeues, &amp; hauing gotten his houſe vpon his head, beginneth to breath himſelfe, and reioyſe, for his good eſcape, thinking all to be ſafe, and ſuſpecting no harme: who coulde ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently bewayle him, if in the middeſt of his Triumphe, they bee founde in his owne houſe, that fall vppon him, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him? And is not the lawe, the houſe of the troubled, and vexed man? Yea, Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter Hal is the poore mans houſe. And therefore doeth he pay taxe, and ſubſidies, that it might bee an houſe of defence vnto him, able to keepe out winde and weather, how tempeſtious ſoeuer. If a man that is
<pb facs="tcp:1505:28"/>oppreſſed, and wronged abroade, in anye part of this lande, ſhall bring his matter vnto hearyng at Weſtminſter Hall, looke that yee bee good vnto him in his owne houſe, let him take no harme at home: His griefe is great enough abroade. It hath alwayes, euen by the lawes of man, beene counted an haynous offence, to vexe and annoy a man in his owne houſe. What ye thynke of the matter, I cannot tell, this I am aſſured of, it is his due, to be well dealt withal there, and yee are to anſweare the Lorde, not onely for denying, but alſo for delaying and deferring of iudgement. For why? the man hath right and title, in his good cauſe, vnto as ſpeedie a diſpatche at your handes, as poſſibly may be had. And therefore <hi>Iob</hi> profeſſed, <hi>that hee had not weeried the eyes of the wydowe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 31.16.</note> 
               <hi>with waytyng long for helpe, before it came.</hi> It is a true ſaying of that Heathen man: <hi>Bis dat, qui citò dat,</hi> He doubleth his gift, that geueth it ſpeedily. It was a griefe to <hi>Iethro, Moſes</hi> his father in lawe, to ſee the people ſtande from morning to euening a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Moſe,</hi> waiting for the diſpatch. How would, hee haue taken it, if hee had ſeene
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1505:28"/>men, (which commonly happeneth heere among vs) to waite fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tearme to tearme, nay from yeere to yeere?</p>
            <p>Wee are all of vs ſeuerally, to deale righteouſly with our brethren, in all our conuerſation with them, and thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, the loue wee beare them. And the Lord hath appointed vs to ſhew this loue, not only vnto them, but vnto the thinges that bee deare vnto them, as goodes, and good name: euen vnto theſe, hath the Lord bounde vs, aſwel as to theyr perſons. For wee muſte thus intermedle one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and finde ſuccour one from another. And theyr name and goodes by his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, goe through our handes and charge, aſwel as his perſon, and muſt finde ſuccour there. This is the charge from our God, that when any thing of theirs paſſeth through our handes, it finde that affection towardes it, which may geue teſtimony of our brotherly good wil to them, and witnes our obedience vnto GOD. And the ſame GOD that forbiddeth the murder of his bodye, forbiddeth alſo the ſtealth of his goodes. And the ſame God that hath bound ouer our loue, &amp; good affection to his body:
<pb facs="tcp:1505:29"/>hath in like maner doone it towardes his goods. Hardly ſhal any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be perſwaded, that he is louing vnto him, who is empay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng him, in any thing that is deare &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious vnto hym, alwayes gayning by his loſſe. The poore man, whoſe money muſte paſſe through the handes of the Merchant, the Farmer, the Draper, &amp;c. By that time that euery one ouerſelling his commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, hath gotten a fleeſe, bryngeth the ſweate of his browes (that is his blood) which he hath plentifully powred out, and made no ſpare of it, throughout the whole yeere, into a narrowe rowme: Neither can hee geue a true report of any loue he found at theyr handes, more then one might finde at the hande of a Turke, or Infidel. In the <hi>25.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> the people of GOD are charged, not to oppreſſe one another, in buying and ſellyng, but as the yeere of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile was nigh, or farre of, ſo to ſell dearer, or better cheape. Wherein the ſeller was bounde, to regarde the profite of him that bought: for longer then the yeere of Iubile he coulde not poſſeſſe it: At which tyme, by the lawe of God it muſt returne to the owner againe. The yeere of Iubile is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1505:29"/>but the law of conſcience (being the equitie of that law) remaineth, that a man ſhoulde regarde, not himſelfe onely, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ſtate of another. Wherby it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, it was not lawfull for a man, to take whatſoeuer he coulde get, without regard, what a hargaine his neighbor was like to haue at his hands. We are exhorted by the Apoſtle, to make conſcience of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in the firſt to the <hi>Theſ. 4.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Let no man oppreſſe or defraude his brother, in any thing, for euen the Lorde is a reuenger of ſuche thinges. Knowe you not</hi> (ſayeth Saint <hi>Paule</hi>) <hi>that the vnrighteous ſhall not inherite the kingdome of God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.</note> And what right hath any man to another mans money, not geuing him the vaiue or worth of it in wares or marchaundize? Bee not deceiued (ſayth the holy Ghoſt in the ſame place.) Neyther Theeues, couetous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nor extorcioners, ſhall inherite the kingdome of GOD. The want of equitie and conſcience in this behalfe, is notably taxed by <hi>Solomon, Prouerb. 20. It is naught, it is naught, ſayth the buyer, but when hee is gone apart, he boaſteth.</hi> It toucheth this naturall corruption, where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="tcp:1505:30"/>man woulde haue regarde onely of him ſelfe, euen without any reſpect of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when not onely his owne thoughtes, but euen his owne wordes, doe oftentimes condemne his dealyng, both of iniurie, and diſſunulation. Our carefull walking in the wayes of righteouſueſſe, haue plentifull promiſes of bleſſing from the Lorde: ſo that if his worde be of any credite with vs, wee may bee well aſſured, that by ſuche dealinges our gaines will growe, to be the greateſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 20.7.</note> 
               <hi>He that walketh in his integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> (ſayth <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>is iuſt, and bleſſed ſhall his children bee after him. He that foloweth after righteouſnes and mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.21.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall finde life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.20.</note> 
               <hi>righteouſneſſe and glory. A faithful man ſhal abounde in bleſſing, but hee that maketh haſt to be rich, ſhal not be innocent.</hi> Men who being greedy of gaine, had ſodainely attained vnto wealth, were the moſt infamous of al other men, euen among the Heathen, ſo that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> grewe with them to be a name of greateſt reproch. A verlet is not more odious with vs, then hee was with them, The order that is heere obſerued, may in no wyſe bee neglected: for ſobrietie is ſet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1505:30"/>before righteouſneſſe in this place: <hi>Wee muſt liue ſoberly and righteouſly</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle.) Without ſobrietie and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, righteous and iuſt dealing cannot be holden vp, and mainteyned: for if a man haue not learned to bee rich, and to be poore, hee ſhall neuer holde out the courſe of iuſtice and righteous dealyng: when it lyeth vppon the loſſe of fauour, eſtimation, credite, wealth, or countenance, to proceede in iuſtice and righteouſneſſe. Hee ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer buie and ſell with conſcience, that hath not accounted with himſelfe to carry a low ſaile, and lower then he hath done, (if God ſee it ſo good.) Wee ſhoulde haue more iuſtice, if wee had more ſoberneſſe in the lande: for if whatſoeuer come, the olde eſtate muſte bee holden, iuſtice and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous dealyng muſt ſome time bee ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. It is this temperaunce and ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that ſtrengtheneth righteous dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng and iuſtice. For yf wee coulde bee content to bee humbled in the worlde, yf GOD coulde not otherwyſe bee ſerued, or a good conſcience maynteyned: wee ſhoulde haue more power to doe iuſtice,
<pb facs="tcp:1505:31"/>and to liue vprightly in our callyng what ſoeuer. But while men are ſo drowned in profites, pleaſures, and honors in the world they are neuer put to any ſtraite, but iuſtice is ſtretched, that the olde compaſſe may be kept, and theyr eſtate vpholden. Let vs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace this temperaunce and ſoberneſſe, ſo ſhall we holde faſt this reine of iuſtice and vpright dealing in our places &amp; callinges. Many good lawes wee haue made, to cauſe vs to liue iuſtly one with another, but litle fruite of them: for why? the roote is not touched. Wee haue taken ſo large a meaſure of port and countenaunce, beeing voyde of this temperaunce, that the cloth muſt needes be cut out thereafter. The ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie that pleaſed our fathers in attire, in faire port, in coſitenance, wil not ſuffer vs, we haue taken a larger meaſure, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt we not ſtretch out the cloth? they haue left vs accordingly. Muſte not our rents be raiſed, our reuenues encreaſed, the priſes of our ware augmented, our paynes dearer, our giftes greater, our pleaſuring of men better conſidered, our paynes more rewarded, our liberalitie to the poore or to any good purpoſe leſſened, our compaſſion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1505:31"/>abated, and ſo our fathers good report de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed? Let euery man caſt more of tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, ſo ſhall he be able to afoorde a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter peniwoorth of righteous and vpright dealing in his callyng whatſoeuer. For ſure, while the meaſure is ſo infinitly inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the cloth muſt needes bee ſet vpon the Tainters, and exceſſiuely ſtretched. It ſhal be in vayne to make lawes againſt iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and vnrighteous practiſes, yf before, this great exceſſe and intemperancie, that ruleth in all eſtates, be not repreſſed. For if that in no caſe may bee abated, howe can it bee but that the olde ordinarie dealinges in righteouſneſſe, and equitie, muſt be rac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked? The great want of ſobrietie that is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where, ſpeaketh that there is muche vnrighteouſneſſe in this land, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently doeth plainly and euidently foretel vs, that the righteous God hath a quarell with the inhabitants of this our countrey, for the vnrighteouſneſſe thereof, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth in euery kyngdome as moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſobrietie abateth. Now how ſobr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie decayeth, and intemperancie is dayly augmented, euen hee that is moſt giltie herein, wil not ſeeme to deny it. Whereby
<pb facs="tcp:1505:32"/>it is euident, that this land ſhal not be able any long time, to beare the vnrighteouſnes thereof. For this great intemperancie tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that the burden of vnrighteouſneſſe which it beareth, is growne to ſuche great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as cannot long be fuſteined, if our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation herein be not ſpeedily attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and taken in hande: which the Lorde in mercy grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, may be throughly thought vppon by you, who haue eſpeciall helpe in your handes to perfourme it.</p>
            <p>Toliue righteouſly is the requeſt of our God: <hi>The grace of God that bringeth ſaluation hath appeared, and teacheth vs to liue iuſtly.</hi> His graces offer them ſelues to take vp theyr conſideration, in our righteous conuerſation, they craue that our vpryght dealyng may ſpeake, in what regarde we haue to them, howe wee thinke our ſelues beholden vnto them, they haue ſet ouer the pleaſuring of them, to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right liuing, there they would haue it ſeene, howe they are valued, pryſed, &amp; eſteemed. Let vs then behold a Chriſtian Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for men of all callynges and trades, when they deale in the woorke of theyr callinges, to moue them to equitie, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1505:32"/>and regarde of thoſe with whom they deale: Beholde, my GOD calleth mee to witneſſe to the worlde, my thankefulneſſe for his benefites, he calleth me now foorth, to value his deſeruinges, now am I called to ſet my price vppon his mercies, and to leaue a recorde behinde me, howe highly or baſely Ieſteeme of his goodneſſe: for the recompence of his kindneſſe hath hee turned and ſet ouer, to be anſweared in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and vpright dealyng one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>The grace of GOD that bringeth ſaluation hath appeared, and biddeth vs liue righteouſly.</hi> Nowe am I to ſignifie vnto the worlde, how I thinke my ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted vnto God, for the benefite of rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the benefice of his word, for honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for health, for children, for friends, peace &amp; wealth: theſe are now crauyng ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. Were it not great crueltie, that crauing ſo litle, they ſhoulde neuertheleſſe be repelled? bringing al things, their conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration ſhould be nothingꝭ Now therfore wil I conſider of my God for this bleſſing, now wil I anſwere in dutiful reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, for that benefit. And ſo draw forth his ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all mercies, to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeuerally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered
<pb facs="tcp:1505:33"/>in our vpright life and iuſt dealing with men. Not with the Papiſtes, to ſeeme to requite him by merite: but with the godly Chriſtian, to ſhew hymſelfe not vnmindfull of them, in humble obedience to his will. Saying after our beſt obedience, with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in the building of the Temple,<note place="margin">1.<hi>Chro.</hi> 29.</note> 
               <hi>Who am I, and what is my people, that wee ſhoulde bee able to offer willingly after this ſort? for all things come of thee and of thine owne hand, haue we geuen thee all this aboundaunce. That we haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to builde the an houſe, is of thy hand, and al is thine.</hi> This meditation is in like maner meete with our croked and diſordered affections, in our dealinges, whiche are voyde of all conſideration of iuſtice, and mercy. While that we ſhall in this maner vrge and preſſe them: doſt thou thus anſwere thy redemption? Is heere the price of thy ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? doſt thou thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite thy ſaluation? is this the thankfulnes for thy health? and al thou mayeſt finde in thy heart to affoorde God of thy wealth?</p>
            <p>It followeth, wee muſt liue godly, this neceſſarily is ioined to righteouſnes. For it were but a vayne thing to bee preciſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1505:33"/>in geuing man his right, &amp; then to withold the Lord his, through impietie. We muſt communicate with him, as I tolde you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his woorde: <hi>Receiue the Lawe of his mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and lay vp his wordes in thy heart. Dauid</hi> hauing declared before how the heauens doe declare the glory of God, and howe the creatures doe leade vs vnto ſome knowledge of him, immediately as one rauiſhed with the maieſtie &amp; excellency of that knowledge of God, which we haue by the woorde, and as one who taketh that other kinde of teaching, to bee nothing in reſpect of this: affirmeth that <hi>the lawe of the Lorde conuerteth the ſoule, &amp; that it geueth wiſdom to the ſimple, geueth light to the eies, and bringeth ioy to the heart:</hi> making theſe to be the ſpeciall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues, of the woord of God, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> neither by the creatures, nor yet by any other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde meanes, may be attained vnto. It behoueth vs therefore, to haue often vſe of the woorde of God, not onely to take our knowledge from thence how to ſerue him: but alſo to ſeeke for incouragement &amp; quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening thereunto from it. For the woorde of God quickeneth vs to our dueties, and
<pb facs="tcp:1505:34"/>ſtirreth vp the ſlowneſſe, that by nature is in vs. A notable example whereof wee haue in the ſecond of the <hi>Chroni.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chroni.</hi> 15</note> 
               <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> We are likewiſe to reſt vpon his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereof he hath made vs ſuch large promiſes in his woorde, to applie his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites as ſpeciall helpes to ſtrengthen our faith, in the perſwaſion of his fatherly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towardes vs, and to prouoke our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience the rather therby, and to be often and earneſt in prayer with him, both to haue our ſtrength and abilitie to ſerue him by that meanes encreaſed: and alſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide that neither by our ſubtile aduerſary, nor yet by our owne frailtie, wee be intrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the net of deſtruction. For albeit by his grace our ſpirite be ready, yet haue we a weake fleſhe, which is to be dragged for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by ſtrength obteyned through pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from our God. Theſe thynges muſt we be geuen vnto, and neyther by a plaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting of them, and erectyng of our owne deuotion: neyther yet by a colde and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe vſe of them, to tempt the Lorde, and to vphold vs in vngodlneſſe, and the fruites thereof. The Papiſtes, Anabaptiſtes, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines, and the Familie of loue, are all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1505:34"/>ſworne enimies vnto godlineſſe, foraſmuch as they will haue the woorde altogeather ſubiect to their ſpirite. For they will haue it not to ſpeake, but as their ſpirite ſhal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, and herevpon they builde, that they are the Churche: and therefore haue a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the holy Ghoſt, to keepe them that they erre not. Enquire of a Papiſt, from whence come theyr vnwritten verities, and many folde traditions, they anſweare, there were many thinges that the Apoſtles then were not able to beare, which the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite being nowe come hath taught them. The Anabaptiſtes, Libertines, and houſe of Loue, vrged with the Scripture, wyll aſke you, what ſayth the ſpirite, affirming that to be but the killing letter. Thus both of them, howſoeuer in other thinges great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly differyng, haue this common principle for their foundation and beginning: that the Scriptures beeing but an ABC to Chriſtianitie, the ſpellyng and readyng thereof muſt be drawne from their ſpirite, as if the Goſpel ſhoulde geue place to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations, and ſo cary with it the ſtayne of imperfection: or as if the ſpirite coulde be diuorſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word, which it was
<pb facs="tcp:1505:35"/>ſent to teache and confirme. As it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.26.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhal bryng al thinges to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, whiche I haue tolde you.</hi> What can be a more ſhamefull abaſing of Chriſte, then to make him but vſher, and their Spirite in place aboue him, chiefe Schoolemaiſters? that as the law brought vs by the hand to Chriſte: ſo Chriſte ſhould be our guide vnto reuelation, and reſigne vnto it, as the laſh did vnto him. They will not deny the word, but in trueth, they make it a matter of nothing. For they will alow no ſenſe vnto it, but ſuche as theyr ſpirite ſhall ſet vpon it. So that in verie deede how ſoeuer they woulde be thought to leade vs to the worde, they doe leade their diſciples, onely to the dreames and deuiſes of their own head. In the time of the law when vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions &amp; reuelations were often and vſual, yet were they then ſubiect to the word, &amp; to be cried by it, nay to be ouerruled of it. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as we reade: <hi>If there ariſe among you a Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Peut. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and geue thee a ſigne or wonder, and the ſigne or wonder which he hath told thee come to paſſe, ſaying: Let vs goe after our gods: thou ſhalt not hearken vnto the words of the Prophet, yee ſhal walke after the Lord your God,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1505:35"/>and ſhall keepe his commaundementes, and hearken vnto his voyce, but that Prophet ſhalbe ſlaine, becauſe he hath ſpoken to thruſt thee out of the waye, wherin the Lord the God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth thee to walke.</hi> If in the times, when viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; reuelations had their beſt alowance, and the moſt lawful title that euer they had: all that notwithſtanding, they were to geue vp their account vnto the written woorde of God, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence to receiue their <hi>Quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt.</hi> We may not then in thoſe times, receiue ſuche wares, vnder the alone war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of their own weights, when faith muſt fight againſt miracles and reuelations, for the woorde, whiche in the infancie of the Church, was helped by miracles vnto the woorde.</p>
            <p>How can there be any true gedlineſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong this people, among whom God is not licenced to ſpeake in his woorde what pleaſeth him, but the woorde ſtrained by their ſpirite, to ſpeake after the liking of miſerable men? Great is the vngodlineſſe likewiſe of thoſe men, who hauing bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſuperſtition and fantaſtical reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet for al that, leaning vnto the hold of their profeſſion of the trueth, as vnto a ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:1505:36"/>fortreſſe: doe not ſubmit themſelues to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny often and earneſt vſe of the woorde and prayer, with conſcience and care to haue theyr wayes reformed by it, and with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of any great neceſſitie that they haue of it.</p>
            <p>We can not geue our ſelues vnto theſe dueties, vnleſſe we ſhalbe in the expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and looking after the hope of an other life, &amp; therfore very fitly doeth the Apoſtle ioine vnto theſe ſeueral duties that we haue hearde of, this ſpeache: <hi>Waiting for the bleſſed hope and glorious appearing of the mightie GOD our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte.</hi> For it cannot come to paſſe, wee ſhould be taken of from things here below, vnleſſe we be aſſured els where. No man wyllet goe thyngs aſſured, for vncertaine. Faith muſt geue vs aſſuraunce of greater glory from GOD, ere wee can let goe the houlde that we haue heere. Therefore it is made a ſpeciall note of God his Children, &amp; neceſſarily ioyned to his worſhip: to be in expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the latter day, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry therof. When <hi>Paul</hi> wil ſet out the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> and fame that was geuen out of them in all places: he doeth no otherwiſe commend them, then
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1505:36"/>that they were turned from idols to ſerue the liuing God, and to wayte for his ſonne from heauen, which ſhould beſtowe vppon them this benefitete, to deliuer them from the wrath to come. And in the ſeconde to the <hi>Theſſa.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.</note> perſwading them by that which was in moſle reuerence and regarde with them, and likeſt to bring them into the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt conſideration of his words: he frameth his ſpeach thus: <hi>I beſeech you brethren by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>and our gathering together and vniting vnto him.</hi> So that the looking for the laſt day, ſemeth to him to be in great reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, regard &amp; aſſured expectation among them when he maketh their reuerence vnto that the matter and ground of this exhortation. And when he laboureth to lift them of the earth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly he reareth them vp with no other inſtrument than this: the waiting for the glory &amp; hope of another life. In the <hi>3.</hi> to the <hi>Col.</hi> he reaſoneth thus:<note place="margin">Colloſ. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>When Chriſt which is your life ſhal appeare, then ſhall you appeare with him in glory, mortifie therfore your earthly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, vncleanes &amp; couetouſnes, which is Idolatry.</hi> And in the <hi>3.</hi> to the <hi>Phil.</hi> opening y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane of their ſtay fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hunting after the earth, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the falſe
<pb facs="tcp:1505:37"/>Apoſtles, which minded earthly thinges: He ſayth thus: <hi>But our conuerſation is in heauen, from whence wee looke for a Sauiour, euen the Lorde Ieſus, who ſhal chaunge our vile body that it maye be like his glorious body.</hi> In the xi. to the <hi>Hebrues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> the obedience of <hi>Abraham</hi> in leauing his owne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, not knowing where he ſhould become, is aſcribed to this that he waited for a Citie that had a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, whoſe maker is God: for al things in the world are ſubiect to corruption. The great things that are ſpoken of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> in accounting the rebuke of Chriſte, to be of more value then the treaſures of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and his not fearyng the fury of the kyng, is onely imputed to this, that he was as if he had ſeene him that is inuiſible. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the glory of that great God, was alwaies before his eies. The greatneſſe of the thing and the excellencie of it is noted in theſe woordes: <hi>The glory of the great God our Sauiour Chriſte.</hi> It is the ſame glory, the great God our Sauiour Chriſte inheriteth, that we waite for. It is worth the waiting for, there is cauſe why wee ſhoulde be mooued to ſobrietie, hauing ſo great thinges in expectation. <hi>We beſeech
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1505:37"/>you</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that ye would walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of god,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>who calleth you to his owne kingdome and glory.</hi> The glory of this worlde deſeleth our eyes, and therfore muſt we be drawne vp by meditation of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thinges, before we ſhall bee able to let theſe be of ſmall reckoning with vs. The greatneſſe of that glory once throughly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, woulde ſet theſe in a baſe and lowe place, it would make them vaniſh asſmoke from our preſence. The expectation of a tranſitorie kingdome, when it is once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured and digeſted by hope, we ſee it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men neglect liues, goodes, landes, friendes, children and countrey to hazarde all. The merchant that is in expectation of ſome great gaine, we ſee into what vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen countreis, into what daungers by the Seas he wil commit himſelfe. The great regarde and care that is had euery where, to the thinges heere below, the greedy fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng after them, the careful purſuing of pleaſures, profites, and honors: do plainly ſpeake, that the hope of another life, is not yet ſetled in the heartes of a great number. Let vs cal to remembrance, how that this is our day to waite, it is our time to ſerue: when Chriſt which is our life ſhal appeare
<pb facs="tcp:1505:38"/>then ſhal we be glorious and appeare with him in glory. There is no pleaſure which the lord hath not matched with ſome griefe and paine, to take of (if it might) our delite, and to faſten it in ſurer thinges. If the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God cannot preuayle with vs, yf it cannot chaunge our taſte, howe ſhall wee looke for renewment? If ſo great hire as is his owne glory, cannot allure vs, brutiſh &amp; ſenſeleſſe muſt our nature needs be. What a greater argument can wee haue of our blockiſhneſſe, then that ſo great things can get no more attendance? The trueth is, we are perſwaded of the excellencie of them, and therefore in all ſuche places alledged for the waiting of his comming: there is the benefit ſet foorth with it, and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, which pointeth at our darkeneſſe and vnbeliefe herein, and telleth vs that the glory of this world, ſtandeth as a cloude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene it and our ſight. To concludle, ſet vs inlarge our hope, &amp; by meditation &amp; praier, enter into ſome conſideration of the length. breadth, and depth, of that glory: ſo ſhal we ſee ſuch a portion in it, as will comfort vs euen in our greateſt afflictions, countiing it a great honour, that we are vouchſafed his ſeruice, as the Apoſtles haue doone.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:1505:38"/>
            <p>Now we are to conſider of that, which is the third thing in this our diuiſion: to wit, what was geuen to make vs good ſchollers in this his doctrine, and to become a people zelouſly geuen vnto good workes. The gift is ſo great as himſelfe, for he gaue himſelf for vs. He laide not downe his life at the pleſure of his aduerſaries, being otherwiſe vnwilling, but franckly and freely of his owne accord did yeeld it vp for vs. This is that which wee eſteeme aboue the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite often times: the minde of the geuer. Great gifts are darkened, when they come from an vnwilling mind, &amp; leeſe their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: but a willyng mind aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth the leaſt gift, that can be. <hi>No man taketh my life fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> (ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt) <hi>but I laid it downe of my ſelfe.</hi> His wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnes alſo appeareth in this, that he went forth to meete them, aſking of them whom they ſought, &amp; confeſſing him to bee a man,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> As his aduerſaries did not compel hym by violence to leaue his lyfe, no more did good deſeruing on our part procure him therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.10</note> And therfore S. <hi>Iohn</hi> doth herein note a ſpeciall thing that he began with vs, and prouoked vs vnto loue, and not wee hym. This loue was voluntarie and not forced.
<pb facs="tcp:1505:39"/>It had likewiſe the preheminence of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and prouoking: and was neither borne nor begotten, of any former benefite of ours to himward. In this gift that was geuen, we are to remember, not onely that moment of his paſſion, wherein hee paſſed immediatly from life to death: but alſo the whole courſe of his life, while he had his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boade with vs heere vppon earth. For hee ſerued vs with his life, as well as with his death: performing in it all that obedience, which the Lord requireth of man. And this obedience vnto the law, could not be vrged of duety vpon hym who was Lorde of the Law, in his owne name, and for himſelfe: but onely in reſpect of vs, whoſe cauſe and perſon he was content to ſuſtaine. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng his life, what a rare argument &amp; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of good wil was this to begin withal: that he would be abaſed ſo farre for vs, as to lay downe the maieſtie and glory, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was nothing inferiour to his father, and to take vpon him the eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a poore and miſerable ſeruaunt, to leaue the higheſt eſtate in heauen, &amp; to goe vnder the baſeſt condition here vpon earth, to chaunge the higheſt dignitie, with the baſeſt condition, the greateſt glory with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1505:39"/>the greateſt infamie: the place that hath ſuperioritie ouer all, with that which is to ſerue all? What is the glory of all king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in the world, if they were ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to the glory of heauen? and yet how impoſſible were it to intreate him, who is king of the leaſte Iſlande in the worlde, to chaunge his eſtate with a ſeruant, to leaue the glory of his kingdome, and to imbrace the eſtate of the meaneſt ſubiect &amp; ſeruant in the land.</p>
            <p>What ſubiect, how friendly ſoeuer in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times he had been to the prince, could after long ſute preuaile thus muche with him? and behold the king of heauen and Lorde of life, doe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, force this friendſhippe vpon his enmies. It requireth our earneſt meditation of the matter, to conſider the greatneſſe of the goodwill that lyeth vnder it: for it hath neuer before or ſince beene hearde of, that the ſonne his lyfe, ſhoulde bee thee price too purchaſe vnto the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt his freedome: that the ſonne ſhoulde be ſolde to ſerue, to the end the ſeruant (nay enemie) might be made free. Wonder at this worke thou earth, and be amaſed at it yee heauens, for from the beginning, if all your regiſters were ſearched, the like ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:1505:40"/>not be heard of at any time to haue happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The gift had bene exceeding great, if we ſhould haue had no more at his handes, then is the ſeruice of his life, lead in all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of obedience for our ſake heere vppon earth: but after this obedience vnto the wil of his father in al duetie accompliſhed, he himſelf muſt paſſe through death, and ſo become a ſlaine ſacrifice for the ſinnes of his ſeruants. Wherin let vs a litle behold the weight of ſuch a work, ſo ſhal we make the better account of hym, who hath wrought it for vs. Let vs behold his behauior, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time approched of his appearing before the iudgement ſeate of the righteous God for ſinners. Which although it be but the entraunce into his paſſion &amp; ſuffering, wyl notwithſtanding let vs haue ſome ſight &amp; taſt, wherby to diſcerne how heard a worke he had in hand. When he was to enter the anſwering of ſinne, he went, as appeareth in the Goſpel after Saint <hi>Mathew,</hi> into a place called <hi>Gethſemane,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.36</note> ſaying to his diſciples, <hi>Sit ye heere, while I goe and pray yonder.</hi> While hee was on the way, he bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to waxe heauy, ſorowful, and greenouſly troubled. Inſomuche that hee (complayning of his griefe vnto <hi>Peter</hi> and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1505:40"/>the two ſonnes of <hi>Zebedeus</hi> whom he toke with him) ſaith vnto them: <hi>I feele my hart heauy vnto death, tarry ye here &amp; watch with me.</hi> The paine preſſed him ſo ſore, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he craueth the comfort of theyr preſence in that combat. Ye may well conſider that it is no ſmall matter, which driueth the ſoone of God, to intreate his Diſciples to watch with him. But are they able to afforde him any helpe? In trueth they can geue no help vnto the matter hee hath in hand. It is no great thing that is required, and yet for all that it cannot bee obteined. It is no great matter to looke on, though the matters which be in doeing, were neuer ſo daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: and yet the Scripture doeth tel vs, that the chiefe of the Apoſtles coulde not holde vp theyr heads, and helpe their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter at his deſire, while hee yet was but in the beginning of his conflict, with ſo much as a comfortable countenance, no not after he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plained of their great vnkindnes, &amp; expoſtulating the matter with them, had vſed theſe wordes towardes them: <hi>What, could ye not watch with me one houre?</hi> A wonderful matter, that <hi>Peter</hi> the prince of the Apoſtles, ſhoulde bewray ſo great weakeneſſe, that beyng ſundrie tymes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted
<pb facs="tcp:1505:41"/>by his maiſter, could not performe towarde our ſaluation ſo litle a matter, as is the looking on. So farre was he from afoording either countenaunce or ſpeache of incouragement, in this cauſe. The Lord had a ſpecial purpoſe in it, and we are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to drawe ſpeciall inſtruction fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, that there did neuer greater wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t appeare, neither moe infirmities breake out of the Apoſtles, then when the worke of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was in hand. For had they geuen but the leaſt helpe vnto that worke, how ſhould men haue beene kept from matching them with Chriſte in the matter of mediation? For many be ſo mad, that notwithſtanding the beſt of them coulde not helpe with a comfortable countenance, when our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was to be procured: yet wil they haue the meaneſt of them, at leaſt felowes with Chriſte at halfe of the Mediatorſhip? for they wyl not be perſwaded, but that they muſt pray vnto them, and ſo haue them fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes with Chriſt in the office of interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Howe hath the holy Ghoſte met with man his infirmitie herein, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued all ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling blockes, that we might haue free paſſage to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alone Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene God &amp; man, the man Ieſus Chriſte?
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1505:41"/>Who can deny but that the only wiſe God did foreſee, what great folly &amp; ſuperſtition many would fal into with the Apoſtles and Saints of God? and therefore would haue the work of our ſaluation ſo cleare &amp; voyde of any helpe from the Apoſtles, that the chiefe of them could not be kept from ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at the beginning: neither from periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp; forſwearing, after a litle farther pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in the ſame. For ſo farre were they from helping our ſaluation forwarde, that being requeſted to watche and ſolace their Maiſter with their ſight in his agonie: that they are daunted, &amp; lie like dead men. And when they are wakened, and reproued for that they would not watch one houre: by &amp; by they fall faſte a ſleepe againe, ſo that no manner of comfort can be had from them. And no maruell, for the Almightie had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bate ſhould be ſingle, perfourmed of one alone, and therefore it could not he, that Peter and Chriſte ſhould ſuffer togither. In deede there were twoo the eues crucified with him, but there was no doubt (which thing the learned doe wel note) that the ſacrifice for ſinne, ſhould haue any ſupply from their ſuffering. The forme of prayer which our Sauiour Chriſt vſed
<pb facs="tcp:1505:42"/>vnto God the father, when he entred into this agonie, doth likewiſe tel vs what pain &amp; anguiſh he did ſuſteine. For ſundry times he made this petition vnto God. <hi>O my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if it be poſsible let this cuppe paſſe from me.</hi> Let vs ceaſſe to maruell that the Apoſtle did beare no part in it, for this his praier doth declare, that Ieſus Chriſt had his hands ful of it. Let vs not maruell why the Apoſtles had no more luſt nor affection to deale in it: for Ieſus Chriſt him ſelf, if he had followed the ſence &amp; perſuaſion of his fleſh, had flatly refuſed it, fainted at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt, &amp; neuer haue gone thorowe with it: <hi>O my father, if it be poſsible lot this cuppaſſe.</hi> Howe heauy a waight of our ſinnes was vpon him, not onely is bewrayed by his praier: but alſo by the drops of bloud that fel from his face, and by his often paſſage, as a man greatly diſtreſſèd and in ſore an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Apoſtles, to the place where he prayed, and from thence, to them again. Sometimes waking them &amp; ſeeking com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from the ſight of them, and ſometimes againe intreating his father for fauour. Neither doth he this once &amp; away, but ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry times doth he renewit, &amp; make ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes to haue eaſe by it. This was the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1505:42"/>beginning of this his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flict much anguiſh was in it, as you haue heard, &amp; litle comfort comming from any, yet the farther he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth, the more his paine increaſeth, and the leſſe comfort he feeleth. Before he had the ſight of his Apoſtles, albeit they could not be kept waking for his comfort, nowe they all flee &amp; forſake him, ſaue Peter, who did abide by it a while, but in the ende did forſweare him. His father whom before he did attempt to intreat, now ſtandeth foorth taking the place of iuſtice, and the ſeate of iudgement, &amp; ſummoneth all his ſeruantes to appeare &amp; anſweré for their ſinnes: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonne of man Ieſus Chriſte commeth foorth to the barre, &amp; appeareth in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of al ſinners, there ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth he to receiue ſentence, and afterwards execution accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, which could be no ſlender puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for it muſt be a ſufficient ſatiſfaction for the ſinnes of all his ſeruantes. It could be no litle blowe that he did beare, for why it was ſuch a one, that the ſinnes of all his ſeruantes did die of it. Howe could it be a little ſtripe or ſtroke, that was the death of ſo manſe ſinnes? Nay vniuerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all the ſinnes in his ſeruantes: When hee went vnder it, this ſpeache of his:
<pb facs="tcp:1505:43"/>
               <hi>[O God, my God, why haſt thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken mee?]</hi> did ſufficiently teſtifie what waight and burden he had of it. Before he was forſaken of men, and his deareſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples had left him: Now ſinne hath ſet his father againſt him, and hee feeleth him an vtter enimie vnto him. For that hee wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not with an ordinarie and vſuall kinde of death, his wordes to his father doo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray. He was to beare the puniſhment for ſinne, which muſt touch him, els how ſhuld we be perſuaded, that the puniſhment was ſufficient, and meete for ſuch a matter. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde a true ballance, wherein to waye ſin, a Glaſſe that will giue vs the true ſight of ſinne. Looke vppon this glaſſe yee, which think that at your laſt houre, ye ſhalde wel enough able to driue away ſin with a ſigh. Behold this ſpectacle, ye that take ſinne in yong men to be the grace of thoſe yeeres: &amp; ſo ſlender a matter in olde men, that it can not abide the leaſt breath, or ſight of one that hath gray heares. You ſee when ſinne is to be anſwered, the Apoſtles left it, and Chriſt him ſelfe did ſundrie wayes declare, that he had enough of it. We may ſee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly by this, that they neuer felt the ſting of it, who in their ſpeeches &amp; remedies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1505:43"/>to redreſſe it, doe giue out ſo ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly of it. There is one thing whereof we are eſpecially to be admoniſhed, that we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer make our ſelues guiltie of ſo great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duettfulnes againſt our God, as to call his diuinitie into queſtion, becauſe he was hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled vnto this anguiſh &amp; paine in our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and bewrayed ſuch ſence and feeling thereof in our nature. For how doe wee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the Lord, if we will let him haue no longer any honour from vs, for that he was ſo greatly humbled for vs? Hereby we may ſufficiently ſee and diſcerne, what a curſed and counterfait Chriſt, that is, which <hi>H. N.</hi> hath brought into the world. For <hi>H. N.</hi> his Chriſt, was not firſt God, &amp; then after whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was to ſuffer made man, but firſt man, &amp; after by his ſuffering, was Godded with God. He gaue no ſpecial argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of good will vnto vs by his paſſion &amp; ſuffering: for himſelfe had the greateſt benefite by it, in ſomuch as that he could not haue bin ſaued without it. He is not this true Chriſte, who offred him ſelfe a ſufficient price, for al the ſinnes of his ſeruantes: for hee leaueth eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to anſwere for his owne ſinne, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him that he him ſelfe and no other is to anſwere for it. And therefore looke what
<pb facs="tcp:1505:44"/>the ſinnes of <hi>H. N.</hi> his Chriſt coſt him, the ſame price muſt they pay for theirs, if they will beleeue him. All the helpe that they haue from him, is that hee hath paide his money before them, ſo that nowe they ſhall not neede to trouble them ſelues, either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the price, to ſpende any long time in learning what is required: neither yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the manner, to vnderſtand where and howe it is to be paide. If any doe meruell howe <hi>H. N.</hi> can make away this ſo plaine an hiſtorie, let them vnderſtande, that it is well knowen to thoſe, who be any thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him, that to ſinke any hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>H. N.</hi> will require no more, then one ſingle ſhot of an Allegorie. The Lorde graunt that they which thus aboliſhe the true Chriſt, &amp; his office, to ſet vp ſo curſed a creature in his place, may be looked to in time before they ſhall drawe others into the ſame condemnation. Chriſt Ieſus gaue him ſelf for vs, to purge vs, that we might be a peculiar people vnto him ſelfe, zealous of good works. Here are all the carnal goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers condemned, who liue in hope, that vnder the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of their profeſſion, all libertie of life, will well enough bee borne out: that make Chriſte his death to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1505:44"/>els, but a bawde vnder their lewde life. Here may we ſee that the Lorde hath not laide downe his life, to purchaſe no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing at our handes, beſide a profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the trueth: but that hee bought with his bloud a zealous addicting of our ſelues to chriſtian conuerſation. It is a wonder to ſee howe the wicked will boaſt of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of Chriſt his bloud, howe mightie it is to merite, howe ſufficient to ſaue from ſinne: But for all that will they not giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer anye libertie of life, that before they haue enioyed: whereas it was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a newe conuerſation, aſwell as a new profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For he gaue him ſelfe for vs, that we might giue ourſelues vnto him, a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar people zelous of good works. Let vs marke it then my brethren, that hee gaue himſelf for vs, to haue the honour of a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian life fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. He left his life for vs, that our life might be let out to honour him. He made not ſo ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der a purchaſe with ſo great a price, as that if he had a good ſigh, or a good worde at our laſt breath, that would ſuffize him: his life was giuen for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of a zealous giuing of our liues to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works that pleaſe him. And therfore doeth the Apoſtle tel vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are not our own me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:1505:45"/>to frame our life after our owne liking, but are to ſerue the Lorde, both with our body and with our ſpirite, becauſe they are the Lordes, bought of him with a price. If we humble not our ſelues to a zealous follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of good works, we withhold the Lords due, for he hath paide a great price, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a good life at our handes. Hee hath with no ſmall price, but dearely bought of vs the honor of a life, led in zealous obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto his word. For we are not barely to giue ſome good words, either els to ſhew ſome good countenance towards religion &amp; chriſtian conuerſation: but to haue our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation declare that we are affected with the ſame, and become ſtudious of ſuch an eſtate of life. Such men declare themſelues to be that peculiar people, for whome the Lorde laide out his life. As for thoſe who walke ſo inidifferently betweene true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and falſe, that a man can not diſcerne whether they are more enclined vnto: As alſo thoſe that walke ſo euen betwene a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill life, and a chriſtianlike behauiour, that the difference is not eaſilie diſcuſſed: they do declare themſelues as yet not to bee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in deſire, toward thoſe duties which the Lord hath laid vpon his. Nowe where
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1505:45"/>this purchaſe of his hath taken place, they are become a peculiar people zealous of good workes. If colde chriſtians haue ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle comfort from the death of Chriſt: what ſhall become of them, that are ſworne eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, either to true religion, or els to good life, &amp; chriſtian behauiour. It is ſaide here by the Apoſtle, <hi>That we muſt be purged, to become a peculiar people vnto our God, zealous of good workes:</hi> which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of purging, the holy Ghoſt performeth not by miracle, but by meanes: wherin we haue great cauſe to be thankfull vnto God, that whereas our foode was exceeding groſſe vnder the gouernment of the Pope, as hauing onely for diet, the inuentions of man: Nowe that pure and fine foode of the worde of God, is not only made lawfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, but alſo liberally laid out for vs. But herein againe, we are both to confeſſe and acknowledge our want, that ſeeing we are not voyd of ſinne, while we remaine in this fleſhe, and therefore haue neede to be often purged &amp; clenſed: our purgations (for all this ſo great a change &amp; ſo good a conſtitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the minde vnder the Goſpel) be now at this day nothing diuerſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe, that were vſed in that great groſſenes which
<pb facs="tcp:1505:46"/>we had vnder the Pope. The Canon lawe (I confeſſe) might purge ſomewhat in thoſe times of ignorance, when becauſe the foode was ſo groſſe, the minde could not but be full of great and grieuous humors: but nowe the conſtitution of our minds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altered, by reaſon that the foode is ſo cleane diuerſe from that it hath bene, howe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it purge to any purpoſe? Let vs therfore euery one pray, that ſeeing by reaſon of this good diet of the Goſpell, the ſtate and conſtitution of our minde is chaunged: in ſteede of the Canon lawe, which paſſeth ouer many daungerous humors, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them neuer a whit, by reaſon of the great groſſeneſſe that is in it: wee may haue rules and Canons out of the worde of God, which will pearce further, &amp; purge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humors, whereof we haue great ſtore, and thoſe ſuch, as do greatly blemiſhe the Goſpel, and cauſeth ſo great ſlaunder vnto our profeſſion, as hindreth many from co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming therevnto. How often doth the whole body of this Realme aſſemble togither in that high court of Parliament, to redreſſe thoſe euils that are amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, either in body goods, or name: making new ſtatutes, and repeling olde, according as by that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1505:46"/>and experience whiche God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them, they ſee and perceyue any daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, either preſent, or ſhortly like to fal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them? But as for the church, which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than maliceth infinitly more, and therefore maketh many ſorer aſſaultes againſt the ſame: how ſlenderly in all ſuch aſſemblies is her eſtate thought vpon? And what ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes are there made, to preuent the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Sathan? Or what olde ones be once repeled, how vnprofitable or hurtful ſoeuer experience doth tell vs that they be? The Lorde touch them with the care of it, who haue eſpeciall authoritie to redreſſe it. I haue already bene verie long, and the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath bene tedious vnto you, a worde therefore or two of the laſt point, and ſo I make an ende.</p>
            <p>The maner of teaching, and trayning of ſchollers in Chriſte his ſchoole, is by tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, exhorting, &amp; rebuking theſe things, ſaith the Apoſtle. <hi>Speake, exhort, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke with al authoritie.</hi> We can not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the matters of ſaluation, by &amp; of our ſelues, they muſt be taught vs, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we yeeld vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in iudgement, being perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth therof: it is another labor the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the former, to be rightly affected w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them.
<pb facs="tcp:1505:47"/>And therefore they muſt be preſſed vppon our affections by exhorting, and rebuking, for we are not by &amp; by truely touched with our duetie, and humbled to the obedience thereof, when once wee haue ſubſcribed in our iudgement, to the trueth and equitie of the thing. Men muſt haue ſpeciall cunning and ſkill from God, that ſhall come within vs, and make vs in iudgement and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to yeelde vnto duetie: howe ſhall they preache (ſaith the Apoſtle) vnleſſe they be ſent? This argueth a ſtrong &amp; a wonderfull corruption to be within vs, which hath ſo blinded our reaſon, and hardened our affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they muſt be men of ſpecial gifts &amp; graces, that ſhalbe able to open the eyes of our mind, to conceiue the trueth, and to touche our affections ſo, as they ſhalbe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to make conſcience of the ſame. Wee may well diſcerne then howe vnprofitable thoſe miniſters be in their place, who know nothing howe to exhort and rebuke. Who would hyre into his harueſt a Mow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that could not ſet an edge vppon his ſith, when it ſhould happen to bee blunted by ſtones or other things, that were hid in the graſſe: And is not teaching exhorting, and rebuking, the edge of the word, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1505:47"/>it cut? And be not our hearts of them ſelues, if Sathan ſhould caſt in no outward occaſions, a grounde that is full of ſtones? And what ſhould he doe then in the harueſt of the Lorde, that can not giue an edge to the worde, by ſtrengthening the trueth of the doctrine, if falſe prophetes &amp; teachers ſhould caſt in ſtones of hereſie, &amp; errenious opinions: nor yet by waking and rowſing the affections of men, by exhorting, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking according to ſounde doctrine, when Sathan ſhall (as hee daily doeth) caſt in great and mightie ſtones of ſecuritie, and hardnes of heart? Now the Seripture hath plainly foretold vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in theſe latter dayes eſpecially, the Lord his field ſhalbe full of ſuch ſtones. It is a matter, that ought to get both teares and prayers from vs, euen in the behalfe of the Lord, as well as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our ſelues: to ſee ſo many vnmeete men in our cuntrey, carie ſithes into the Lords harueſt, who when once they meete with any ſtoppe, and be ſet but a litle beſide their booke muſt be forced to rethrne home with their ſithes vpon their ſhoulders, and let the Lords medon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue, vntill it ſhal be withered, or eaten vp of the aduerſarie.</p>
            <p>The Lord giue them heartes to thinke
<pb facs="tcp:1505:48"/>of it: whoſe labour although it were but a litle, might do great good for the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. And as the Churche hath a great plague of theſe men, ſo hath it of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort, who haue giftes, and are wel able teach, and to exhort, but yet for all that they wyll not abide &amp; bee reſident vppon theyr flockes, to diſcharge that duetie in theyr owne perſons, but careleſly committe them ouer vnto others. An offence that in the greateſt darkneſſe of Popery, hath ben founde faulte withall among them ſelues, and taken to haue beene the onely decay of theyr kingdome. And therefore a pitifull thyng it is, that in this light of the Goſpel it ſhoulde not be acknowledged, that there is great ſinne in ſuche thinges. <hi>Eſpenſaeus</hi> a Popiſh Prelate, affirmeth that a famous Preacher of his time, did oftentimes thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der out againſt thoſe men, that ſo careleſly ſet ouer their charges vnto others: telling them plainely, that the Lorde would ſerue them in the worlde to come, according as they did ſerue him here: <hi>Adibunt per vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios Paradiſu: in perſona, inferos.</hi> The Lord (ſayth he) will ſend ſuch men to heauen, by Vicars, and to hell, in their owne perſons.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1505:48"/>He confeſſeth that the Preacher, did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly denounce ſuch iudgementes againſt them: <hi>Solitus eſt palàm illis polliceri vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam ſalutem, perſonalem verò perniciem.</hi> Others ſhal goe to heauen for them (ſayth he) for as for themſelues in their owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they muſt be of neceſſitie reſident, vnto a perſonage of theyrs in Hell, whiche is called perdition. The ſpeache as hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, is ouer pleaſaunt, for ſo weightie &amp; graue a matter, as alſo for ſo heauy &amp; hard iudgement. God graunt that ſo pleaſaunt ſpeach, may ſinde gentle and courteous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, with ſo many as ſhalbe found fault heerein. Wel, ſo great is the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our nature, that wee haue neede of diligent teaching, exhorting &amp; rebuking, if we ſhal yeeld any glory vnto our God, or good example to our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To conclude therefore, (for I haue ſtonde long, and am afraid, haue weried you as wel as my ſelf.) The Lord of al Maieſtie &amp; power graunt, that as Chriſte Ieſus, when hee came into the worlde, founde the Sheepheardes of <hi>Iurie,</hi> carefully looking to theyr flockes: ſo when hee ſhall come againe too iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hee maye fynde thoſe Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes, who haue his Churche, and choſen
<pb facs="tcp:1505:49"/>people for their flocke, ſo diligently watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp; faithfully attending ouer the ſame: as that by the meanes therof, he may haue great glorie from his people, by plentifull fruites of godlineſſe, righteouſneſſe, and ſobrietie: and that the Goſpell being in all places thus glorified, our conſciences may be truely comforted in Chriſt Ieſus. To whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, one true and euerli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, be al honor, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and dominion, both nowe and euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by <hi>Thomas Dawſon, dwelling</hi> at the three Cranes in the Vinetre for Richard Sergier. 1579.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1505:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
